<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Words whereby we may be saved. By Thomas Vincent, sometime minister of Maudlins milk-street, London</title>
            <author>Vincent, Thomas, 1634-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V452A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230467</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896290</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896290</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154091</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95931)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154091)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2396:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Words whereby we may be saved. By Thomas Vincent, sometime minister of Maudlins milk-street, London</title>
                  <author>Vincent, Thomas, 1634-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 84 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the use of the poor, and freely given to them by some worthy benefactors, who desire their salvation,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154091:1"/>
            <p>WORDS WHEREBY We may be Saved.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS VINCENT,</hi> ſometime Miniſter of <hi>Maudlins Milk-ſtreet, LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Act. 11. 14.</bibl>
               <p>Who ſhall tell thee Words whereby thou and all thy Houſe ſhall be ſaved.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Heb. 2. 3.</bibl>
               <p>How ſhall we eſcape, if we neglect ſo great ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, which began to be ſpoken of by the Lord, and was confirmed unto us by them that heard him?</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the uſe of the Poor, and freely given to them by ſome worthy Benefactors, who deſire their Salvation. 1668.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:154091:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154091:2"/>
            <head>To the POOR.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe few ſheets were chiefly intended for you; and therefore I thought fit in a few lines to dedicate them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you. Some Benefactors give you Food, others give you Raiment, others give you Money; all which gifts are for the relief of your temporal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, and of concernment only to your bodies. Here you have a gift in order to the relief of your Spiritual neceſſities, a Soul-gift, which doth concern your ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And as the Soul is more excellent than the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and the Salvation here treated of, is of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more value than all earthly Riches: So in ſome meaſure of proportion you ſhould prize ſuch gifts chiefly as are for the good of your Souls, and may be (through Gods bleſſing) a help to you in the attaining of Salvation. Your ſouls are as precious as the ſouls of the moſt honourable; and your ſouls whileſt in a ſtate of nature, are in as great danger of ruine, as the ſouls of the moſt ſinfull; and though you ſhould be as yet out of a ſtate of Salvation, you are as capable of obtaining ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation as the moſt holy before Converſion. And for your further encouragement I may tell you, that you may get to Heaven without ſo great difficulties as the Rich: See <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. 24. and <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. 5. you have not thoſe ſnares and temptations in your way as the Rich have; which as it ſhould quicken your endeavours after, ſo it will aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate your ſin if you ſhould neglect your ſalvation.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:154091:3"/>
            <p>Wicked rich men have their good things here, ſome kinde of Portion in this life, and their evil things are chiefly reſerved untill hereafter; But you which are Poor have little portion of good things in this life, and if you do not obtain ſalvation, you will have no good things reſerved for you in the other World, nothing but treaſures of wrath according to your treaſures of ſin; and ſo beſides the miſeries you undergo here, you will be miſerable hereafter, and miſerable for ever. My hearts deſire and prayer for you is, That you may be ſaved; therefore have I written theſe things. You have this little Book freely given unto you by ſome Worthy Perſons, who hope for a fuller reward than the price of any Books can amount unto; eſpecially if this Book be made uſe of by the Lord as a means for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion and ſalvation of any of your ſouls, their reward will be the greater that have been inſtrumental here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; therefore accept of this Gift, read it in your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, or get it read to you where you cannot read your ſelves. But chiefly accept of the Salvation this Book ſpeaketh of, which, however dearly purchaſed by the blood of Chriſt, is freely tendered unto you. Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a Gift, and the greateſt, moſt excellent, and moſt neceſsary Gift; to move and guide you in the obtaining of which, is the deſign of theſe ſheets; which that they may be ſucceſsfull, is the Prayer of a dear Lover of, and Well-wiſher to the Poor.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Vincent.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154091:3"/>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE chief end which every one ought to intend in his Life, is the Glory of God, and the Salvation of his own Soul: The chief work of Miniſters is to tell People words whereby they may be ſaved: Such words <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh to <hi>Cornelius, Act.</hi> 11. 14. and ſuch words I ſhall endeavour in theſe ſheets to tell ſinners.</p>
               <p>In order to your ſalvation, I ſhall ſpeak,
<list>
                     <item>1. Some Words to try you whether you be in a ſtate of Salvation.</item>
                     <item>2. Some Words to move you to endeavour after your Salvation.</item>
                     <item>3. Some Words to guide you in the way to attain Salvation.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <div type="section">
                     <p>I. The firſt words ſhall be to <hi>try you,</hi> whether you be in a ſtate of Salvation; and here I muſt put you upon the tryall of your ſelves, wherein I may give you ſome help; take the Exhortation of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5. <hi>Examine your ſelves, whether ye be in the Faith, prove your own ſelves.</hi> Examine your ſelves by the Rule of the Word: And becauſe theſe Words are chiefly intended in order to the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of ſuch as have not yet attained it; to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them for the following Motives and Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which, if they miſtook themſelves to have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready attained to a ſtate of ſalvation, would likely
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154091:4"/> do them no good: Therefore I ſhall briefly out of the Word of God give</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Some Characters of ſuch as are not in a ſtate of Salvation.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Ignorant perſons</hi> are not in a ſtate of ſalvation. See this <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27. 11. <hi>It is a people of no underſtanding, therefore he that made them will not have mercy on them, and he that formed them will ſhew them no fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour:</hi> Thoſe that are groſly ignorant of the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Truths of Religion, concerning God and Chriſt, the loſt eſtate of Man ſince the fall, the way of Salvation, Repentance, Faith, the Reſurrection from the dead, the laſt Judgement, and the future Rewards and Puniſhments in Heaven and Hell, and the like Principles of Religion, which are neceſſary to be known in order to ſalvation, they cannot for the preſent be in a ſtate of Salvation; the meaneſt underſtanding is capable of knowing theſe things by the teachings of the Word and Spirit, therefore ſuch as do neglect the means of Inſtruction, and do not ſearch the Word, and cry to God for it, but nuzzle up themſelves in an affected ignorance in theſe things, are inexcuſable in their fault, and will bring unavoidable deſtruction upon themſelves, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4. 6. <hi>My people are deſtroyed for lack of knowledge.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>Negligent perſons</hi> are not in a ſtate of ſalvation, I mean ſuch as neglect their ſalvation. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 3. <hi>How ſhall we eſcape if we neglect ſo great ſalvation?</hi> Such as do not value and prize this great ſalvation purchaſed by Chriſt, and publiſhed in the Goſpel; ſuch as never were made ſenſible of their need here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; ſuch as never had any great deſires after it;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:154091:4"/> ſuch as never took any pains in the uſe of means to obtain it; all which are evidences of their neglect, they cannot eſcape the dreadfull puniſhment of Hell, which is prepared for ſuch perſons. Such as are diligent to make proviſion for their Bodies, but neglect the ſalvation of their ſouls; if they perſevere in this negligence they muſt needs miſs of ſalvation.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>Impenitent perſons</hi> are not in a ſtate of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Luk.</hi> 13. 3. <hi>Except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.</hi> All are guilty of ſin original, and actual, and have matter for repentance; ſuch as have an obdurate and impenitent heart, which never was broken, and melted, and humbled; which never was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with true evangelical ſorrow for ſin; but on the contrary, can commit ſin with delight, rolling it as a ſweet morſel under their tongue, which they will not part withall, they muſt needs periſh everlaſtingly, if they ſhould die in this eſtate; the word is expreſs, that iniquity will be the ruine of the impenitent, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. 30.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregenerate perſons</hi> are not in a ſtate of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 3. <hi>Except a man be born again, he cannot ſee the Kingdom of God.</hi> Such as never had a gracious change wrought in their hearts, that are aſleep in ſin, and never were awakened; as are dead in ſin, and never were quickened; ſuch as have old natures and old hearts, and never were renewed; that never put off as concerning their former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation the old man which is corrupt, according to deceitfull luſts, and put on the new man, which is created in righteouſneſs and true holineſs, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 22, 24. they are uncapable whileſt ſuch, of this ſalvation, there is no entrance for them into the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:154091:5"/>
                     <p n="5">5. <hi>Chriſtleſs perſons</hi> are not in a ſtate of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5. <hi>Know ye not your own ſelves, that Jeſus Chriſt is in you, except ye be Reprobates.</hi> Such as have not Chriſt, and are not themſelves in Chriſt, they are for the preſent in a ſtate of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation; It is Chriſt only can ſave; thoſe that are without Chriſt, that are not united to him by Faith and the Spirit, that are Unbelievers without Faith, and carnal without the Spirit, they cannot, whileſt ſuch, be ſaved.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſanctified perſons</hi> are not in a ſtate of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 14. <hi>Without holineſs none ſhall ſee God.</hi> Such as are unholy, ſuch as live after the fleſh ſhall die, none but thoſe that through the Spirit do mortifie the deeds of the body ſhall live, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 13.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. And in a word, <hi>Diſobedient perſons</hi> are not in a ſtate of ſalvation. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 9. <hi>He became the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Eternal Salvation to all them that obey him,</hi> to none elſe; and <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 6. <hi>The wrath of God cometh upon the Children of diſobedience.</hi> Such as walk in a courſe of diſobedience, as live and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low themſelves in the practice of known ſins, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they be, they are children of wrath becauſe children of diſobedience. The Scriptures are ſo plain, that I need without many words of mine, only lay them before you, as a Glaſs wherein you may diſcern your ſpiritual ſtate. Try your ſelves by theſe places, theſe Texts will reach all that are not in a ſtate of ſalvation.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:154091:5"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <p>II. <hi>THE ſecond words ſhall be to move you to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour after your Salvation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Motives to ſtir up you to endeavour your ſalvation may be drawn,
<list>
                        <item>1. From the conſideration of your ſelves, Whom you ſhould endeavour the ſalvation of.</item>
                        <item>2. From the conſideration of the ſalvation which you ſhould endeavour to obtain.</item>
                        <item>3. From the conſideration of the Damnation of all ſuch as do not obtain ſalvation.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <div n="1" type="motive">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Motive</hi> 1. From the conſideration of your <hi>ſelves,</hi> whom you ſhould endeavour the ſalvation of: It is the ſalvation of your ſelves, which I would preſs you unto; It was the exhortation of the Apoſtle, Phil. 2. 12. <hi>Work out your own ſalvation with fear and trembling,</hi> and this is my exhortation of you this day, Labour after your own ſalvation: If I were to perſwade you to do ſome great kindneſs for another, were it a difficult thing and like to coſt you much labour and trouble, I ſhould not likely prevail; but when I am perſwading you to do a kindneſs for your ſelves, and the greateſt kindneſs in the World, even to endeavour after the ſalvation of your ſelves; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks the natural Love which you bear to your ſelves ſhould induce you to hearken and do what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is requiſite in order hereunto, though it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done without difficulty and trouble. How far will carnal ſelf-love carry carnal men? what
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154091:6"/> difficulties will they go thorow? what expences of time and pains and ſtrength will they be at? how will ſome riſe up early and ſit up late, deny themſelves food and reſt and many comforts of this life? how will others compaſs Sea and Land and hazzard life it ſelf, and all to get an eſtate in the world for themſelves? and ſhould not ſpiritual ſelf-love, which is the only reall ſelf-love, carry you thorow difficulties? ſhould you think much of exſpending time and pains that you may get ſalvation for your ſelves? carnal ſelf-love will bring deſtruction and miſery upon ſuch as are ſwayed by it, and in the iſſue will prove ſelf-hatred; as you really love your ſelves, as you would eſcape the moſt dreadful mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and obtain the chiefeſt happineſs for your ſelves, labour after ſalvation for your ſelves. Your ſelf, your Perſons do conſiſt of two parts, namely, Soul and Body; it is the ſalvation of both, which I exhort you unto.</p>
                     <div n="1" type="section">
                        <p>1. Conſider, it is the ſalvation of your <hi>Souls</hi> which I would have you endeavour after, the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of your precious ſouls; your ſouls are more precious than your bodies, and they are more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious than the whole world.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. Your ſouls are more precious than your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, they are by far your more excellent part: the original of your ſoul is more immediately from God: he formeth the ſpirit of man within him, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12. 1. they are beams, they are ſtreams that iſſue forth immediately from God; moreover they carry more of the impreſs and image of God upon them as they are inviſible, ſpiritual, rational, free, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal; they have alſo more high and excellent operations than the body is capable of, as of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:154091:6"/> underſtanding, conſcience, memory, will, affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and I may add that if there be any luſtre upon the body, it doth receive it from the ſoul, when the ſoul is gone, the beauty is gone; whatever mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or uſe there is in the body, it doth depend on the ſoul; when the ſoul is departed, the body can neither hear, nor ſpeak, nor ſee, nor walk, nor do any buſineſs; the body is a rotten ſtinking carkaſs without the ſoul; and whileſt the ſoul doth abide in it, the body is the inferiour part, the body is but the Cabinet, the ſoul is the Jewel; the body is but the houſe of clay, the ſoul is the living inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant; the body is as it were the beaſt (as one ſaith <hi>Corpus homini jumentum</hi>) which the ſoul doth make uſe of to carry it from one place to another; the body is the ſervant, it is the ſoul that rules, O labour then after the ſalvation of your ſouls, which are your moſt excellent part; what care do ſome take to preſerve their bodies? much more reaſon have you to endeavour the ſalvation of your ſouls: when <hi>London</hi>'s Fire was burning the houſes, thoſe who could not ſave all their goods, took care to ſave thoſe which were the moſt precious, eſpecially their money and jewells; O whatever become of your bodies here, whatever ſickneſs or hardſhip they be expoſed unto, labour to ſave your jewels, your precious ſouls; the Cabinet will be ſpoilt, the clay and mudd-wall will be broken down, and the ſoul will ſurvive the body; O take heed that when your ſouls come forth of their houſes of clay, that they be not caſt into the deep and dark priſon of Hell.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Your ſouls are more precious than the whole world; our Saviour eſteem'd them ſo, and he beſt knew the worth of ſouls, who knew the making
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154091:7"/> of them, and made purchaſe of ſo many loſt ſouls, ſee Matth. 16. 26. <hi>What is a man profited, if he ſhall gain the whole world, and loſe his own ſoul? or what ſhall a man give in exchange for his ſoul?</hi> Suppoſe that you had your hearts-deſire in the world, that your baggs ſhould throng in your Coffers, till there were no more room; your gold and ſilver ſhould encreaſe without number; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you had great poſſeſſions abroad, large revenues, ſtately houſes, fruitful gardens and orchards, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant groves and walks, ſpacious fields and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, which as the Poet ſaith, would weary the wings of a Kite to fly over in a day; ſuppoſe that you had ſweet and beautiful wives at home, like loving Hindes and pleaſant Roes unto you, like fruitful Vines about your houſes; that you had towardly and hopeful Children like Olive-plants round about your Tables; that you had moſt kind and faithfull friends of moſt pleaſant converſation; that you had ſervants, horſes, chariots, coaches, doggs, hawks, and all ſorts of ſerviceable and delightful creatures, the beſt and in the greateſt number at your commands to attend your pleaſure: ſuppoſe you were cloathed with purple, wrapped in fine linnen, adorned with gold and ſilver, and preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtones, and had the moſt rich and glorious Attire that the greateſt coſt and art could make for you: ſuppoſe that your food were moſt delicious, that Aire, Earth, and the Sea were ranſack'd to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide dainties for your Table; that your courſes were ſerved up with the moſt rich and generous Wine, the moſt ſweet and harmonious muſick: ſuppoſe that you were laden with titles of honour, and had all the Crowns and Scepters of the earth laid
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:154091:7"/> at your feet, and that the whole world had you in the higheſt eſteem, and were in willing ſubjection unto you; yet what would it profit you to gain all theſe things, or any thing elſe that the heart of man could deſire in the world, and loſe your ſouls, which are a thouſand fold more pretious: the gain of theſe things are but for the body, and but for a while; whereas the loſs of the ſoul is for ever; and when the ſoul is loſt, all is loſt; when the ſoul leaveth the body, a period is put to all earthly enjoyments; and the more you have of theſe things, the more grievous will it be to part with them; Think with your ſelves that you muſt dye certainly, and may dye ſuddenly, and then, if not before, you will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the worlds vanity and the preciouſneſs of your ſouls, which are of longer duration than the age of ten thouſand worlds put together, and what is the gain of the world which is ſo tranſitory and temporal, in compariſon with the loſs of the ſoul which is immortal, and whoſe loſs is irrepaira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: a loſs in the eſtate may be recovered, Riches may fly away upon the wing, and ſometimes return upon the wing again, as in the caſe of <hi>Job;</hi> but the loſs of the ſoul can never be recovered; when once the ſoul hath taken wing and is fled into the lower regions, it will never find wings to return again to its former eſtate: O therefore whatever you loſe, take heed you do not loſe your ſouls, your ſouls are very precious, ſeek after their ſalvation.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="section">
                        <p>2. It is the ſalvation alſo of your <hi>Bodies</hi> which I would have you endeavour after: I do not mean the ſalvation of your bodies from ſufferings, which Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion doth ſometimes call you unto; nor a ſalvation of your bodies from ſickneſs and temporal death,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154091:8"/> which Religion doth not exempt any from; but the ſalvation of your bodies from perpetual death and pain of Hell; you may pamper your fleſh for a while on Earth, which may make it a more fit bait for the Worms in the grave, and your bodies after death may be at reſt, and take a ſweet ſleep for many years in the duſt; but there is a morning approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after the long night of death and many hours of darkneſs, in which the graves will be opened and the dead will be awakened, and then your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies will come forth of the duſt; and they will be adjudged by Chriſt unto moſt horrid and endleſs tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in Hell, to burn for ever in unquencheable Fire, if you be found under the guilt of ſin: O there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore labour after the ſalvation of your Bodies; when your bodies now are ſick, you endeavour to get them cured, when they are full of pain, you uſe means to get the pain removed; and you will fly as faſt and as far as you can from natural Death, and you will do much to lengthen out and ſtrengthen the thred of your life, though do what you can, it will in time be cut aſunder, and death which hath you up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the chaſe will overtake and overcome you what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever reſiſtance be made; O labour to get deliverance from the pains of body which are prepared in Hell for the damned: Fly, O Fly from eternal Death and the ſtrokes of Gods wrath which will come upon the bodies of the wicked hereafter; if you would not have thoſe faces ſcorched, thoſe eyes and tongues and hands roſted, and that fleſh broiled and fearfully tormented in the flames of Hell fire, labour after ſalvation. As you love then your ſelves, your ſouls and bodies, ſeek after your ſalvation.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:154091:8"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <div n="2 cont." type="part">
                  <div n="2" type="motive">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Motive</hi> 2. FRom the conſideration of the <hi>Salvation</hi> which you ſhould endeavour to obtain; and here I ſhall ſet before you ſome properties of this ſalvation to move you the more effectually to ſeek after it.
<list>
                           <item>1. It is a great Salvation.</item>
                           <item>2. It is a rare Salvation.</item>
                           <item>3. It is a neceſſary Salvation.</item>
                           <item>4. It is a poſſible Salvation.</item>
                           <item>5. It is a neer Salvation.</item>
                           <item>6. It is an evident Salvation.</item>
                           <item>7. It is a free Salvation.</item>
                           <item>8. It is a ſure Salvation.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <div n="1" type="property">
                        <p>I. It is a <hi>great</hi> Salvation, and that both in regard of the thing it ſelf, and in regard of the cauſes of it.</p>
                        <div n="1" type="section">
                           <p>(1.) It is great in regard of the <hi>thing it ſelf.</hi> As in Motion, ſo in Salvation there is the <hi>terminus à quo,</hi> and the <hi>terminus ad quem,</hi> the term from which, and the term to which; that which people are in Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation delivered from, and that which in Salvation they attain unto, both which are exceeding great.</p>
                           <p n="1">1. That which people in Salvation are delivered from.</p>
                           <p>There are ſix great evils which thoſe that are ſaved are delivered from.</p>
                           <p>1. From ſin, the greateſt evil of all, from the guilt of ſin, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 7. and the power, the reigning power of ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6 14. 2. From Sathan the greateſt enemy of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154091:9"/> all, from his power and tyranny, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 13. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 26. 3. From the Law, the evil which it occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneth, namely, the provoking to concupiſcence and diſobedience, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 5, 6. and the evil which it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth, namely Gods curſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 10, 13. 4. From the world, not in regard of their place, but in regard of their courſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 4. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 19. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. 16. 5. From Death, the ſting of death, and the fear of death, at leaſt the grounds of fear, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 14, 15. 6. From wrath, the wrath of God which is to come, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 10.</p>
                           <p n="2">2. This Salvation is great in regard of that which in Salvation people do attain unto. All the priviledges of the Goſpel are wrapt up and included in the word Salvation. Election is the foundation of it; Effectual calling is the begining of it; Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, Adoption and Sanctification are contained in it, and Glorification is the conſummation of it. This Salvation then is great in regard of the thing it ſelf.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="section">
                           <p>(2.) This Salvation is great in regard of the cauſes of it.
<list>
                                 <item>1. Efficient.</item>
                                 <item>2. Meritorious.</item>
                                 <item>3. Inſtrumental.</item>
                                 <item>4. Finall.</item>
                              </list>
                           </p>
                           <p n="1">1. This Salvation is a great Salvation in regard of the <hi>efficient cauſe,</hi> and that is God the Father: Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is aſcribed to him as the author, Tit. 3. 5. <hi>According to his mercy he ſaved us.</hi> God is the cauſe of our Salvation, 1. as he hath choſen us unto Salvation, Eph. 1. 4. <hi>As he hath choſen us in him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the foundation of the world:</hi> which Election be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Free grace, we are ſaid to be ſaved by Grace, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2 5. 2. As he hath ſent his only begotten Son into the world, to purchaſe Salvation for us,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154091:9"/> Joh. 3. 16. <hi>God ſo loved the world that he gave his only begotten Son that whoſoever believeth in him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life.</hi> Gal. 4. 4, 5. <hi>When the fulneſs of the time was come God ſent forth his Son, made of a Woman, made under the Law, to redeem them which were under the Law, that we might receive the Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of Sons.</hi> 3. As he revealeth this Salvation unto us by the Preaching of the Goſpel, for which end he qualifyeth and ſends his Miniſters upon this Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to make known the glad tydings of Salvation. 4. As he conferrs Salvation actually upon us in our effectual calling, Juſtification, Adoption, Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Glorification, all theſe are from God. Now that muſt needs be a great Salvation which is effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the great God, eſpecially if we conſider that it is the greateſt and moſt glorious of all his works in the world, and unto which all his other works have ſome kind of tendency.</p>
                           <p n="2">2. This Salvation is a great Salvation in regard of the <hi>meritorious cauſe,</hi> and that is the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the excellency and greatneſs of whoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, office and ſufferings do demonſtrate the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Salvation which was purchaſed by him. The ſufferings of Chriſt were moſt properly the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious cauſe of mans ſalvation, and they were the greateſt ſufferings that ever were endured, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as 1. They were the ſufferings of the greateſt perſon; as man he was the head of the creation in regard of dignity, he was a greater King than <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, Matth.</hi> 12. 42. a greater Prophet than <hi>Moſes, Heb.</hi> 3. 3. a greater Prieſt than <hi>Aaron,</hi> even a Prieſt after the order of <hi>Melchiſedec, Heb.</hi> 7. Moreover he was God as well as man, God manifeſted in the fleſh, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16. and though the God head could
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:154091:10"/> not properly ſuffer, yet through its union in the ſame perſon to the Manhood, it put an efficacy in his ſuffering, and ſtrengthened the humane nature to undergo greater ſufferings as to the value of them in that ſhort ſpace of time, than all the Angels and Men in the world (had their ſtrength been united toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one perſon) could have endured, if the greateſt extremity of miſery had been layd upon ſuch a one unto all eternity: For 2. The ſufferings of Chriſt were equivalent unto eternal death, and the torments of the damned in Hell, yea they were far exceeding, as is evident, becauſe Gods infinite Juſtice is hereby fully ſatisfied, and there is ſufficiency of merit in them for the redemption of the whole world not only of Believers, but alſo of Unbelievers, not only of Men but of Devils too: Chriſts ſufferings were of infinite value, not in regard of the ſufferings but in regard of the Divine nature ſo cloſely united unto the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature: Therefore the ſalvation purchaſed by theſe ſufferings muſt needs be a great ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                           <p n="3">3. This ſalvation is a great ſalvation in regard of the <hi>Inſtrumental Cauſe,</hi> and that is Faith; faith is a grace of great worth and excellency, inſomuch as it doth not ſpring from any root or power of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but is wrought by the power of God, and requireth ſuch exceeding great power in the effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it; we read of the exceeding greatneſs of Gods power towards them that believe according to the working of his mighty power, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 19. which ſhews that the ſalvation is great which is ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by this grace of Faith.</p>
                           <p n="4">4. This ſalvation is a great ſalvation in regard of the <hi>Final Cauſe,</hi> and that is the manifeſtation of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:154091:10"/> Gods glory: 1. The glory of his Wiſdom in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving ſuch a way for Mans ſalvation, which no created underſtanding could have thought of: 2. The glory of his Juſtice which is as fully ſatisfied through Chriſts ſufferings, as if all Believers had been eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally puniſhed: 3. And chiefly the glory of his free grace and mercy, which is ſet forth and magnified ſo eminently in all the degrees of mans ſalvation, that nothing may be aſcribed unto Man, but all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God alone.</p>
                           <p>Thus you ſee, that this ſalvation is a great ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in regard of the <hi>Thing</hi> it ſelf, and in regard of the <hi>Cauſes</hi> of it. It is ſo great ſalvation as it hath no compariſon, and is beyond expreſſion, therefore labour to attain this ſalvation; ſome endeavour to get a great Eſtate, others to get great Friends, others to get great honour and repute in the world, do you labour to obtain this great ſalvation which doth exceed all in greatneſs, it is a high and noble deſign, and is worthy your uttermoſt care and diligence in ſeeking after it; other things are but ſmall things, meer toyes and trifles in compariſon; nothing in the world hath the leaſt degree of worth, compared with this ſo great ſalvation. I ſhall be more brief in ſpeaking of the other properties of this ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="property">
                        <p>II. This ſalvation is a <hi>Rare Salvation:</hi> I mean, that few do obtain it; Many are called, few are choſen, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20. 16. Many are damned, few are ſaved: There are many troops of ſinners that are proſting in the broad way of deſtruction, it is but a thin ſcattered company that are preſſing forward in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154091:11"/> the narrow way of life and ſalvation; this is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from the Anſwer of our Saviour upon the Queſtion propounded unto him, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13. 23, 24. <hi>Then ſaid one unto him, Lord are there few that be ſaved? And he ſaid unto them, Strive to enter in at the ſtrait gate, for many I ſay unto you will ſeek to enter in, and ſhall not be able.</hi> In which words he doth in effect ſay, that Few, very Few ſhould be ſaved, for he tells them plainly, that the gate of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is a ſtrait gate, and many cannot paſs tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a ſtrait gate; and although many ſhould ſeek to enter in at this gate, yet they ſhould not be able; and if many that ſeek to enter in ſhall not be able, then it follows, that none of thoſe which do not ſeek to enter in ſhall be able: Hence then we may gather a ſtrong argument to prove, that very few ſhall be ſaved; If the moſt of men and women in the world do not ſeek ſalvation at all, and they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly attain it, and many that ſeek ſalvation ſhall never finde it, then there are but few that ſhall be ſaved; but the moſt in the world do not ſeek ſalvation at all, to ſay nothing of the Heathen world which is by many degrees the far greater part of the world, who ſit in darkneſs, and from whom the Goſpel of ſalvation is hid, and therefore are expreſly ſaid to be loſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 3. Even in the Chriſtian world where the light of the Goſpel doth ſhine, the moſt of men and women, that bear the name of Chriſtians, are ignorant, or profane, or only civil and morall, and live in the total neglect of the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Goſpel, and ſuch cannot poſſibly attain ſalvation that do not at all ſeek after it: And of them that make ſome profeſſion of Religion, and do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in order to ſalvation, many ſhall not be able
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154091:11"/> to attain it; our Saviour ſaith, that many ſhall ſeek to enter in and ſhall not be able, becauſe they do not ſeek in a right manner, becauſe they do not ſeek ſalvation chiefly; they ſeek the ſatisfaction of their luſts, before the ſalvation of their ſouls; becauſe they do not ſeek it diligently, they are careleſs and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal in the uſe of the means of ſalvation; they ſeek, but they do not ſtrive to enter in at the ſtrait gate; they do not preſs towards the mark for the prize of the high calling, and therefore they fall ſhort and miſs of it; there are but few that ſtrive to enter in at the ſtrait gate, that ſtrive as wreſtlers in wreſtling, or racers in running, or warriours in fighting, as the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> doth ſignifie; few that ſeek their ſalvation above all other things, and with all their heart and might, few that are reſolved for ſalvation whatever it coſt them, whatever they do, or ſuffer for it, unto which reſolution and endeavour all muſt come, or elſe they cannot be ſaved, and theſe being ſo few, certainly there are but few that ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. More plainly our Saviour ſpeaks to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Math.</hi> 7. 13, 14. <hi>Enter ye in at the ſtrait gate, for wide is the gate and broad is the way that leadeth to deſtruction, and many there be which go in thereat; becauſe ſtrait is the gate and narrow the way which leadeth unto life, and few there be that finde it.</hi> The gate and way of ſin which leads to death and Hell, are wide and broad, and the moſt in the world are paſſing thorow this gate, and walking in this way; the courſe of the world is a courſe of ſin, the end of which courſe is deſtruction, and the reaſon why ſo many go in at the gate of ſin; which is the outer gate of Hell, is, becauſe ſtrait is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>, and narrow the way which leadeth unto life;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:154091:12"/> becauſe of the difficulties in the way of life and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, which require much pains and diligence if we would go thorow them; we muſt give all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, if we would make our calling and election ſure, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 10. We muſt work out our ſalvation with fear and trembling, if we would attain ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 12. we muſt labour if we would enter into Reſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 12. we muſt ſtrive if we would enter in at the ſtrait gate, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13. 24. we muſt run if we would obtain the prize, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 24. we muſt fight the good fight of Faith if we would lay hold on eternal life, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 12. the Kingdom of Heaven ſuffereth violence, ſaith our Saviour, and the violent take it by force, <hi>Math.</hi> 11. 12. we muſt lay ſiege to Heaven, if we would take it, and with force and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence overcome thoſe potent enemies, the Devil, the Fleſh, and the World, who would draw or drive us away from the walls and gates of the New <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi> It is not an eaſie thing to be ſaved, the way to Heaven is narrow, and it lyeth up hill, our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours for Heaven eſpecially at the firſt, are like climbing up a ſteep hill, like hewing a way thorow hard rocks, like ſwimming againſt a ſtrong ſtream, like cutting hard wood againſt the grain; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the oppoſition and difficulty in the way of ſalvation, therefore there be but few that finde the path thereof; moſt chooſe a broader and eaſier way. It is evident then from what hath been ſaid, that this ſalvation is Rare and ſcarce, the conſideration whereof ſhould not diſcourage you, but quicken you unto the greater diligence in your endeavours after it; the rarity of it ſheweth the worth and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of it; Jewels and precious ſtones are rare and hard to be got; what difficulties will ſome
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:154091:12"/> thorow? what dangerous voyages unto the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt parts of the Earth will ſome undertake, to bring home ſome rare things? but eſpecially the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration withall of the neceſſity of ſalvation (of which in the next particular) ſhould quicken you to ſeek after it. Think with your ſelves (my beloved) think ſeriouſly, and think frequently, that there are but few that ſhall be ſaved; and then examine, what reaſon you have to think that you are in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe few: When our Saviour told his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples that but one of them ſhould betray him, they looked one upon another, and every one asked him, <hi>Lord is it I?</hi> there was none of them without their fears which made them ſo inquiſitive, and they ſeem to be in pain untill they are reſolved; what then would they have thought and ſaid? how fearfull would they have been, if our Saviour had told them that the moſt of them ſhould have betrayed him, yea that all of them ſhould betray him, but one? May not I without uncharitableneſs ſay, that not one in twelve, no nor one in twenty, no nor one in a hundred in this City and Nation ſhall be ſaved? If I ſhould tell you that hear me this day, that ſome of you will be damned, yea that many of you will be damned, yea that m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> of you will be damned, and that but few of this great company will be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ſhould I be a falſe Prophet? I will not ſay it will be thus, neither can I do it, becauſe this is Gods ſecret; much leſs do I deſire it ſhould be thus, for the end of my preaching is, that you all might be ſaved; but let me tell you, that I fear that many of you here preſent will be found in the number of thoſe many our Saviour ſpeaketh of, that ſhall ſeek to enter in at the ſtrait gate, and ſhall not be able;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:154091:13"/> our Saviour told his Auditors, that flocked to hear him, thus, and are you better than they? you all ſeek to enter in at the ſtrait gate, by coming into this place where the Goſpel is preached, and where the gate is ſet open before you; but are there not many amongſt you that ſeek in a careleſs and negligent manner? May not I ſay of all the ſeekers here, that there are but few that ſtrive to enter in at the ſtrait gate? Do you all, or the moſt look as if you had your eye upon the mark and glorious prize before you, and were preſſing with all your might towards it? do you hear as if it were for your lives, as if you might hear words this day whereby you may be ſaved? do you pray and ſeek as if you were in earneſt, as if you were reſolved to take Heaven by violence, and whatever you were denyed in, would not be denyed your ſalvation? Such as do not ſtrive ſhall never get thorow the ſtrait gate. Think with your ſelves, It may be that many in this place ſhall be damned, and then ſay, Shall not I? ſhall not I? and O what a miſerable wretch ſhall I be if I ſhould be damned! if I ſhould get only to the gate of Heaven, and not get thorow! if I ſhould come only to the borders of the Heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> and dye in the Wilderneſs! if I ſhould be found in the number of the negligent ſeekers which will miſs of ſalvation? What grounds have I to think that I ſhall be ſaved? there are but few, can I think that I am inthe number of the few? Methinks this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the Rarity of ſalvation ſhould awaken you to give earneſt heed that with the moſt that ſeek it, you may not miſs of it.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="property">
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:154091:13"/>
                        <p>3. This ſalvation is a <hi>neceſſary ſalvation:</hi> the great difficulty of obtaining ſome precious things diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageth the endeavours of the moſt in ſeeking after them, eſpecially when they may be well enough without them; but this ſalvation is neceſſary, you cannot be without it; it is of abſolute and univerſal neceſſity; ſome things you may have, this you muſt have; without it you are undone, you will be irrecoverably and eternally miſerable; there is no <hi>medium,</hi> no middle condition between ſalvation and damnation (of which more by and by): ſome things are neceſſary to the body, but ſalvation is neceſſary to your happineſs, without it there is no poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity (in this fallen ſtate) of obtaining the chief end, the chief good which you are capable of; without this no coming neer to God in whom your chiefeſt happineſs doth conſiſt, no viſion or fruition of him either in part here, or in full and eternally hereafter. Some men have need of one thing, and ſome of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but all the men and women in the world have need of ſalvation, becauſe all are ſinners, all are children of wrath by nature. There is not one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon amongſt you all but have been guilty of ſin, for the whole world is guilty before God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 19, and every moment of your lives you are expoſed unto the puniſhment of ſin in Hell, unleſs you are brought into a ſtate of ſalvation. It is neceſſary therefore that all of you ſhould above all things ſeek after your ſalvation.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="property">
                        <p>4. This ſalvation is <hi>a poſſible ſalvation;</hi> though there were never ſo much worth and excellency in, never ſo much neceſſity of this ſalvation, yet if there
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:154091:14"/> were an impoſſibility of obtaining it, all arguments would be uſed in vain to preſs any to endeavour after it; but this ſalvation is poſſible, it is poſſible that <hi>you</hi> ſhould attain it, that the meaneſt of you, the vileſt of you, yea that every one of you that hear theſe words may attain it.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. The <hi>meaneſt</hi> of you may attain this ſalvation, and that 1. Such of you as are of the meaneſt parts, though you have neither humane learning, nor ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity or ability for it; though your judgement be ſhallow, your fancy and invention dull, your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory weak, and so could never underſtand and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the many Arts and Sciences in Philoſophy, and the divers kinds of Languages, which learned men have written their books in; yet you are capable of being made the Schollars and Diſciples of Jeſus Chriſt, and he can teach the dulleſt and ſhalloweſt of you all the deep myſteries of ſalvation by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; yea and he can give you a greater underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in them, than the wiselt and moſt learned men that are without the Spirit do attain unto; For he hideth thoſe things from the wiſe and prudent which he revealeth unto babes, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. 25. And the natural man, let him be never ſo learned a man, receiveth not the things of the Spirit, neither can he know them because they are ſpiritually diſcerned, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14. And therefore when not many wiſe men after the fleſh are called, God chooſeth the fooliſh things of the world to exalt the riches of his free grace in their ſalvation, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 26, 27, 31. <hi>Surgunt indocti &amp; rapiunt coelum, quum nos cum omni doctrina in Gehenn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap> detrudimur,</hi> ſaith one. The un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned ariſe, and take Heaven by violence, when we with all our learning are violently thrown down
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:154091:14"/> into Hell. So that you who are of no learning, and but mean natural abilities, have encouragement to ſeek after this ſalvation of the Goſpel, ſeeing the Lord can teach you by his Spirit, and it doth bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuit with his deſign of glorifying his free grace in beſtowing it upon ſuch as you, rather than on the wiſe and learned men of the world, who would be apt to aſcribe the glory unto themſelves. 2. Such of you as are not only of the meaneſt parts, but alſo of the meaneſt condition in the World, may attain this Salvation; <hi>the poor have the Goſpel preached unto them,</hi> Matth. 11. 5. If with poverty in regard of Eſtate, you are alſo poor in ſpirit, the riches of grace and ſalvation are tendered free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unto you; read for your encouragement what the Apostle ſaith, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. 5. <hi>Hearken my beloved Brethren, hath not God choſen the poor of this World, rich in Faith, and Heirs of the Kingdom, which he hath promiſed unto them that love him.</hi> If you were to ſeek ſome great favour from an Earthly Prince, your mean attire and condition might keep you at a diſtance; and you might have no regard given to your requeſt, ſhould it have a hearing; The Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions of the great and rich are heard in Courts on Earth, when the poor and mean are deſpiſed: but the King of Heaven doth regard the rich no more than the poor, <hi>Job</hi> 34. 19. And if you ſeek diligently after this Salvation, you may have as free acceſs to the Lord as any, and your Petitions shall be heard in the Court of Heaven, and you ſhall certainly obtain this Salvation which you ſeek after.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. The <hi>vileſt</hi> of you all may attain Salvation; Some of you it may be have been notorious ſinners,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:154091:15"/> your conſciences do accuſe you of ſuch great ſins, with ſuch hainous aggravations, that you may be diſcouraged and out of hope that ſuchas you ſhould be ſaved; you have offered ſuch high affronts and indignities unto the higheſt Majeſty that you think he can never put them up; you have run ſo deep and ſo long upon the ſcore, that you think the ſcores can never be wiped off; if they had been ſmaller faults, or more ordinary ſlips, or you had ſought after Salvation ſooner, you might have hoped to ſpeed, but now you fear the door of mercy is ſhut, and the day of Grace is ſpent, and there is no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and ſalvation for ſuch vile ſinners as you: But let me tell you that the vileſt of you all may attain Salvation, the door of mercy is not ſo faſt ſhut as yet, but by knocking hard it may be opened; and ſo long as the day of your life is continued, and the means of grace are continued, you cannot ſay that the day of grace is quite ſpent; there is ſalvation attainable by the worſt of you all, if you will look after it; our Saviour tells us of Publicans and Harlots that entred into the Kingdom of Heaven ſooner than the Phariſees who boaſted in their own righteouſneſs, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. 31. He converſed with, and called the worſt of ſinners to repentance, <hi>Matth.</hi> 9. 11, 13. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed when the Apoſtle maketh mention of notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſinners, he telleth us, that ſuch whileſt ſuch, could not be ſaved, 1 Cor. 6. 9, 10. <hi>Know ye not that the unrighteous ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God, Be not deceived, neither Fornicators, nor Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, nor Adulterers, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ffeminate, nor Abuſers of themſelves with Mankind, nor Thieves, nor Covetous, nor Drunkards, nor Revilers, nor Extortioners, ſhall inkerit the Kingdom of God.</hi> Thoſe that are ſuch no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:154091:15"/> ſinners, and continue in the practice of ſuch ſins without repentance, they cannot be ſaved; but withall he addeth in the 11. <hi>verſe,</hi> that ſome of them had been ſuch ſinners, but were now in a ſtate of Salvation through their intereſt in Jeſus Chriſt, and the operation of the Spirit of God upon their hearts, <hi>And ſuch were ſome of you; but ye are waſhed, but ye are ſanctified, but ye are juſtified in the name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the ſpirit of our God;</hi> they were juſtified, their ſins pardoned and perſons accepted, in the name of the Lord Jeſus, through the imputation of his righteouſneſs unto them, and they were waſhed and ſanctified by the Spirit of God, through infuſion of Grace by the Spirit into them: I might add further inſtances of notorious ſinners who have been ſaved, as <hi>Manaſſes, Mary Magdalen, Paul,</hi> who before Converſion calleth himſelf the chiefeſt of ſinners, yet obtained Mercy and Salvation; and let me tell you moreover, that if you repent now and apply your ſelves to Chriſt, the greater your ſins have been, the more will Gods glory be illuſtrated in your Salvation, and the abounding of your ſins will make way for the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abounding of his grace.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. All of you that hear theſe words may obtain Salvation, it is poſſible that every one of you in this place may be ſaved; it would be a rare thing, but it is a poſſible thing: indeed there are but few that ſhall be ſaved; but who knoweth but all of you may be found in the number of thoſe few; and O how would it rejoyce my heart to ſee all thoſe faces in Heaven whom I ſee here this day to hear the words of Salvation. Be encouraged to ſeek after your ſalvation by the poſſibility of obtaining. <hi>Now</hi>
                           <pb n="26" facs="tcp:154091:16"/> ſalvation is poſſible for all of you that have not as yet attained it; but let me add, that it will not be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible long for you all; whilſt you are in the land of the living it is poſſible, though you be condemned to Hell for ſin whilſt unbelievers, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 18. He that believeth not is condemned already; yet the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of condemnation is traverſible, you may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal from the Court of the Law, to the Court of Chancery; you may fly from the bar of Gods ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, unto the throne of grace; and if you heartily repent of ſin, and by faith lay hold on Chriſt, you may obtain pardon and ſalvation: Whilſt the reprieve of your life laſteth, ſalvation is attainable; but when once your life is come to an end (which you know not how ſoon it may be) and you be found in a ſtate of impenitency and unbelief, then the percullis will be ſhut down upon you for ever; then the black flag will be hung out; then the talent of lead will ſeal up the meaſure of your wickedneſs; and your condemnation will be irreverſible; when the day of your life is ſpent, the day of grace will be ſpent too, and the door of mercy will be ſhut upon you for ever; and it will be impoſſible for any of you that have not attained, then to attain ſalvation.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="property">
                        <p>5. This ſalvation is a <hi>neer Salvation.</hi> Say not in your heart, Who ſhall aſcend up into Heaven to learn what it is there? or who ſhall deſcend into the deep to bring notice of it from thence? or who ſhall take the wings of the morning, and fly into the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt parts of the earth thence to bring tydings of it to you? for the word of ſalvation is near unto you, it is brought home to your own doors, it is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:154091:16"/> that word which is now ſounding in your cars, even the words which we Miniſters preach unto you: read what thoſe words are which are brought ſo nigh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13. <hi>The word is nigh thee, even in thy mouth, and in thy heart, that is the word of faith which we preach, That if thou ſhalt confeſs with thy mouth the Lord Jeſus, and ſhalt believe in thy heart that God hath raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved: For with the heart man believeth unto righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and with the mouth confeſſion is made unto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. For the Scripture ſaith, Whoſoever believeth on him ſhall not be aſhamed: For there is no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Jew and the Greek: for the ſame Lord over all is rich unto all that call upon him: for whoſoever calleth upon the Name of the Lord ſhall be ſaved.</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore ſalvation was only amongſt the Jews, and whoever of other Nations would be ſaved, they muſt travel to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and worſhip the Lord in his Temple, and enquire for ſalvation in that place: then ſalvation was afar off from the Gentiles, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially from theſe Brittiſh Iſles; but now ſince the revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, as thoſe which were afar off are made nigh by the blood of Chriſt; ſo the word of ſalvation is brought nigh unto us; you have many Meſſengers of Peace, which bring the glad tydings of ſalvation near unto you, and this may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther encourage you to ſeek after it.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="property">
                        <p>6. This ſalvation is an <hi>Evident Salvation:</hi> I mean, that it is more clearly and evidently made known un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, than it hath been in former ages unto any, or than it is in other places unto many.</p>
                        <p>In former ages this ſalvation was not made known
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:154091:17"/> ſo clearly unto any, I mean in the ages before the coming of Chriſt: the Prophets themſelves who propheſied of it, did not fully underſtand what the Spirit in them did ſignifie, when it foretold of this grace which ſhould come unto the Church in after ages, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 10, 11. And therefore the firſt preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel of ſalvation, is called a revelation of the myſterie which had been kept ſecret ſince the world began unto that time, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 25. And a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of that myſterie to the Saints which had been hid from ages and generations, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 25, 26, 27. The Goſpel of ſalvation was indeed revealed in the diſpenſation of the Law upon Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> by <hi>Moſes,</hi> but it was more obſcurely; it was wrapt up in types and figures; and as there was a vail before <hi>Moſes</hi> his face, ſo there was a vail before the truths of ſalvation, ſo that the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> could not ſtedfaſtly look unto the end of thoſe things which were after to be aboliſhed, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 13. but this vail is done away in Chriſt, <hi>v.</hi> 14. When Chriſt ſuffered upon the Croſs, the vail of the Temple, which kept the people off the Holy of Holies, was rent from the top to the bottom of it, and then the way into the Holy of Holies was made manifeſt, and Chriſt by his appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance aboliſhed death, and brought life and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality to light by the Goſpel, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 10. Then dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs did paſs away, and the true and marvellous light did ſhine upon the Church, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 8. And now with open face believers do behold as in a glaſs the glory of the Lord, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 18. The ſcope of which places is to ſhew the obſcurity of former reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and the clearneſs and evidence of the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Goſpel in theſe latter daies.</p>
                        <p>In other places this ſalvation is not made known ſo
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:154091:17"/> clearly unto many; it is not made known at all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the moſt in the world; a thick darkneſs of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance doth overſpread the greateſt part of the face of the earth, and even amongſt thoſe that call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by the name of the Church of Chriſt: there are in many places ſuch fogs and miſts of errour and hereſie, that the truths of ſalvation are darkened, and peoples minds are blinded; but now unto you this ſalvation is made ſo clear and evident; the thing and way of it is made ſo manifeſt, that it is a great encouragement to ſeek after this ſalvation.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="property">
                        <p>7. This ſalvation is a <hi>Free Salvation;</hi> it will coſt you no money, you may have it for nothing, you may have it for accepting: If you were taken captive by men, if you were ſlaves to the Turks, poſſibly you might not be delivered without ſome conſiderable ſumm for your ranſom; but you may be delivered from the ſlavery of the Devil, and your own luſts, you may be ſaved from ſin and Hell without money: Indeed a price hath been paid for your ranſom, not ſilver or gold, but that which is ten thouſand times more precious, and that was the blood of Jeſus Chriſt, which was ſhed upon the Croſs for you; yet though your ſalvation coſt Chriſt dear, it is free unto you, it will coſt you nothing; pardon is free, and grace is free, and eternal life unto you is a free gift; you are invited to come unto the waters, and to buy wine and milk, but it is without money and without price, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. 1. The Spirit faith, come, and the Bride faith, come, and whoſoever is athirſt let him come, and take of the waters of life freely, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 17. There is ſufficiency of grace in God for
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:154091:18"/> the ſalvation of you all, and you may come and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of this grace in your ſalvation freely: You may have it without money, if you be poor; the gifts of God cannot be bought; and you may have it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out merit; if you conceit that you deſerve any thing, you ſhall be ſure to have nothing; if you are ſenſible of your unworthineſs, and apply Chriſts merits and righteouſneſs, through him you may have ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion freely.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="property">
                        <p>8. And laſtly, This ſalvation is a <hi>Sure Salvation;</hi> you have the promiſe of God for it, and there can be no greater certainty of a thing than the word of God, eſpecially if you conſider that God is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite in power, and therefore can do whatever he will, and that God is infinitely true, and therefore will do whatever he hath promiſed: God is moſt powerful, and therefore able to ſave you; there is ſtrength ſufficient in his Almighty Arm, to bring ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation unto you; and God is moſt faithfull in the promiſes of ſalvation, which he hath made in the Covenant of Grace; if you get faith to apply the promiſes, you ſhall certainly have the thing: There is an uncertainty in every thing elſe in the world, but there is a certainty in this ſalvation; that there is ſuch a thing is certain from the revelation of the Word of God, who cannot lye; and that you may have it if you will accept of it, is certain from the nature and firmneſs of the promiſes; and when you have attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto any degrees of this ſalvation, the perfecting of it will be moſt ſure; for he that hath begun a good work in you, will perform it until the day of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 6. Thus I have laid before you the properties of this ſalvation; it is a great ſalvation; it is a rare ſalvation; it is a neceſſary ſalvation; it is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:154091:18"/> a poſſible ſalvation; it is a near ſalvation; it is an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſalvation; it is a free ſalvation; it is a ſure ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; all which being laid together, may be a ſtrong motive and inducement to you to labour that you may attain a ſhare in this ſalvation.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <div n="2 cont." type="part">
                  <div n="3" type="motive">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Motive</hi> 3. FRom the conſideration of the <hi>Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of all ſuch as do not obtain ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The damnation of all ſuch perſons will be <hi>Dreadfull</hi> and <hi>Certain.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <div n="1" type="section">
                        <p>(1.) The Damnation of ſuch as are not ſaved will be dreadful.
<list>
                              <item>1. The Day of their damnation will be dreadful.</item>
                              <item>2. The Sentence of their damnation will be dreadful.</item>
                              <item>3. The Execution of their damnation will be dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</item>
                           </list>
                        </p>
                        <p n="1">1. The <hi>Day</hi> of the damnation of ſuch as are not ſaved will be dreadful, and that is the laſt day, the day of judgement: O how dreadful will this day be to you that are wicked and ungodly, when the Heavens ſhall be opened, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Judge of the world ſhall deſcend with a ſhout, with the voice of the Arch-Angel, and the loud ſound of a Trumpet; when the Earth ſhall be opened, and you ſhall be raiſed out of the duſt, and ſummoned to appear before Chriſts Tribunal; and the Books ſhall be opened, and all your ſins ſhall be made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt before the whole world; when the Heavens ſhall be on fire, and melt down upon you, and paſs away with a great noiſe; and the Earth ſhall be on fire, and burn under you; and every Mountain and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:154091:19"/> Hill ſhall flee away before Chriſts face; and Chriſt ſhall be on fire, and come in flames of anger to take vengeance upon you for your ſins. Think, O think how dreadful this day of damnation will be unto all ſuch of you as ſhall not then be found in a ſtate of ſalvation! O what dread will ſeize upon you ſo ſoon as your eyes are opened, and you find the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions of the word which you formerly ſlighted to be true, and perceive that now indeed the day of Gods wrath is come, when you ſhall be dragged like ſo many malefactors before the Judgement-ſeat, and there ſtand naked horribly laſhing your ſelves in the reflections of conſcience upon your fore-paſt wickedneſs; how will you be ready to tear your ſelves to pieces for your folly and madneſs, that you did not provide for this day, and flee from this wrath of God, which then you will not be able to eſcape? how willingly would you creep into ſome rock, or under ſome mountain, or abide ſtill in your grave, or caſt your ſelves into the Sea, if poſſibly any place could be found to hide you in this terrible day, but ſhall be able to finde no hiding-place for your ſelves? Think what hideous thoughts, what ſinking fears, what horrible perplexity of mind you will on this day be filled withall, it will be a dreadful day.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. The <hi>Sentence</hi> of the damnation of ſuch as are not ſaved will be dreadful; when the Books are opened where your ſins are recorded, and you are convicted by the Judge; then he will proceed to paſs ſentence upon you. <hi>Depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels, Matth.</hi> 25. 41. O dreadful words! the voice will be loud with which they will be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, ſuch as ſhall reach the cars of all the wicked
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:154091:19"/> together of all generations, and how will they all quake and tremble at the ſound thereof! You may cry it may be to the Lord for mercy, but it will be in vain; you may ſay, Lord open to us, and receive us into thy Kingdom, that we may participate in the joyes thereof; but he will ſay unto you, Depart from me, I know ye not all ye workers of iniquity: But if you muſt depart, you may wiſh for his bleſſing, as <hi>Eſau,</hi> though it were but an inferiour bleſſing; no, depart ye curſed, depart with a curſe: If then you muſt depart with a curſe, you may wiſh for ſome convenient place of abode, and good company, as <hi>Cain,</hi> when he went forth from the preſence of the Lord with a curſe, he built a City to dwell in, and took ſome comfort, it may be in his habitation, and wife, and children; no, depart into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels; you muſt dwell in devouring fire, and inhabit everlaſting burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and your companions will be the Devil and his Angels, and fellow-damned ſinners, in whom you will not find the leaſt comfort, which leads to the third particular.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. The <hi>Execution</hi> of the Damnation of ſuch as are not ſaved, will be dreadful, and this will be in Hell; when the irreverſible ſentence of damnation is paſſed upon you, immediately the execution will follow, and you will be haled from the Judgement ſeat, and the everlaſting doors of the priſon of Hell will be lifted up, where a horrible fire is burning, which can never be quenched, into which you muſt enter, and be ſhut down, and ſhut in to take up your eternal abode in that place of torment; there every part will be tormented, every member of your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, every faculty of your ſouls, and that in the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:154091:20"/> higheſt degree of extremity beyond your now ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, and your torments will have no intermiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, neither will you have any hopes of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion. I have already treated in my Book of Judgement of the univerſality, extremity, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the torments of the Damned, and therefore ſhall not here inlarge. From what hath been ſaid, you may evidently perceive, that the Damnation of ſuch as are not ſaved will be dreadfull, which ſhould awaken you to endeavour after your ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, eſpecially if withall you conſider,</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="section">
                        <p>(2.) That the Damnation of ſuch as are not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved will be <hi>Certain;</hi> where there is no Salvation there will be unavoidable Damnation, becauſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe two hereafter there will be no middle condition; ſuch as are not ſaved will moſt certainly be damned; Heaven or Hell, eternal happineſs, or eternal miſery will be the portion of all the Sons and Daughters of <hi>Adam.</hi> I might ſhew, that Gods Juſtice, and Holineſs and Truth, doth require the Damnation of all ſuch as do not obtain Salvation by Jeſus Chriſt, ſo that either God muſt prove un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy, and unjuſt and falſe in his Word, which is impoſſible, or you which are not ſaved muſt be damned; therefore this is moſt certain, there is no eſcaping of the damnation of Hell by ſuch as neglect the great Salvation of the Goſpel, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 3.</p>
                        <p>And methinks by this time I ſhould hear ſome of you cry out as the <hi>Jews</hi> when <hi>Peter</hi> preached, or the Jaylor, <hi>O what ſhall we do to be ſaved?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:154091:20"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <p>III. I Am to tell you <hi>Words to guide you in the way to attain Salvation.</hi> And here I ſhall
<list>
                        <item>1. Direct what things you muſt do, that you may be ſaved.</item>
                        <item>2. Shew what Means you muſt make uſe of to help you in thoſe things.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <div n="1" type="section">
                     <p>I. What Things you muſt do that you may be ſaved. Take this in theſe Ten Directions.
<list>
                           <item>1. You muſt ſee your ſelves loſt.</item>
                           <item>2. You muſt mourn for ſin.</item>
                           <item>3. You muſt turn from ſin.</item>
                           <item>4. You muſt believe in Jeſus Chriſt.</item>
                           <item>5. You muſt get a new Nature.</item>
                           <item>6. You muſt lead a New Life.</item>
                           <item>7. You muſt reſolve upon ſufferings for Chriſt, if called.</item>
                           <item>8. You muſt ſtudy and apply the Promiſes of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace.</item>
                           <item>9. You muſt give up your ſelves in Covenant unto God.</item>
                           <item>10. You muſt be ſtedfaſt and perſevere in the Wayes of God unto your lives end.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <div n="1" type="direction">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Direction</hi> 1. <hi>You muſt ſee your ſelves loſt,</hi> if you would be ſaved; <hi>Luk.</hi> 19. 10. our Saviour telleth us, <hi>that he came to ſeek and ſave that which was loſt.</hi> You muſt be loſt if you would be found: We read <hi>Luk.</hi> 15. of the loſt Sheep, the loſt Groat, and the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:154091:21"/> loſt Son, all which were found again, and that with joy. When ſinners perceive themſelves to be loſt and undone, and know not what to do, then they are neer to be found and ſaved by Jeſus Chriſt: O then as ever you expect Salvation by Chriſt, you muſt ſee and be ſenſible of your loſt eſtate, whileſt you are in a ſtate of Nature: And for this end you muſt get a Conviction,
<list>
                              <item>1. Of your ſin.</item>
                              <item>2. Of the Puniſhment you have deſerved for your ſin.</item>
                              <item>3. Of your Inſufficiency to ſatisfie Gods Juſtice.</item>
                              <item>4. Of your inability to make reſiſtance, and defend your ſelves.</item>
                              <item>5. Of the Impoſſibility of your fleeing and eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Gods wrath.</item>
                              <item>6. That as yet you have no Intereſt in Chriſt, who alone is able to deliver you from the wrath to come.</item>
                           </list>
                        </p>
                        <p n="1">1. That you may be ſenſible of your loſt eſtate, you muſt get <hi>a Conviction of your ſin,</hi> your eyes muſt be opened to ſee your ſelves guilty of ſin before God, and your mouths muſt be ſtopped, ſo as to have nothing to ſay if the Lord ſhould condemn you. You muſt not only underſtand the nature of ſin in the general, that it is a tranſgreſſion of the holy, and righteous, and good Law of the holy and glorious God of Heaven and Earth; but alſo you muſt be particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and thorowly convinced, that you have tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed this Law of God; you muſt be convinced of your particular ſins: As to the kinds of your ſins, you muſt 1. See your ſelves guilty of <hi>Original ſin,</hi> of <hi>Adams</hi> firſt tranſgreſſion by a juſt imputation, you being in his loyns, and parties in the firſt Covenant: and then you muſt ſee what inherent ſin there is in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:154091:21"/> your nature, that you were conceived and born in ſin, that you are a viperous brood, a Serpentine ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, a ſeed of evil doers; that the Toad is not fuller of poyſon, than your natures are full of ſin; that your natures are contrary unto the nature of God, and have an enmity in them againſt the Law of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 7. You muſt be convinced, how your natures are depraved, being wholly deſtitute of Original Righteouſneſs, empty of all good, and inclinable wholly unto evil; that they are a pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted fountain, from whence can proceed nothing but what is unclean; that they are a bitter root, from whence doth ſpring forth ſuch curſed fruits of ſin in your lives; and you ſhould look upon your ſin of nature to be the worſt, becauſe the Original of all actuall tranſgreſſions. 2. You muſt be convinced of your <hi>actual ſins,</hi> how you have broken Gods Law in thought, word and deed, you muſt ſee your ſins of Omiſſion, and your ſins of Commiſſion, againſt the firſt and ſecond Table of the Law, and take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the number of them, ſo far as you can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, together with their aggravations; if they have been committed through ignorance when you have had means of knowledge, if againſt light of Nature and the Word, if againſt the reluctance of natural Conſcience, if againſt many Warnings and Reproofs, if they have been committed with ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, hardneſs of heart, delight, greedineſs, pride, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, obſtinacy, and the like; and that you might be convinced of the guilt of ſin, you muſt look into the Law, in which as in a glaſs you may ſee your natural face, and all the ſpots thereof; the Law will diſcover the ſin of your natures, as it requireth perfect conformity thereunto in habit, diſpoſition,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:154091:22"/> and inclination, and forbiddeth all evil byaſſes of the will and heart to ſin, as well as external tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions; Moreover the Law will diſcover to you your actual ſins; but then you muſt look beyond the head Precepts of the Law, which are but ten, for you muſt take notice of the ſeveral branches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to every head, which are many; as for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, If you would finde out whether you are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Adultery, you muſt not only look upon the Precept as forbidding only the groſs outward act; <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery,</hi> but as reaching to the inward deſires and inclinations, and ſo our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 28. interprets this Precept, that whoſoever looketh upon a woman to luſt after her, hath committed Adultery with her already in his heart; and ſo in the Precept, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> it is murder not only to take away the life of another by violence, but alſo to be angry with our brother without a cauſe; and ſo in the other Precepts. And as you muſt look into the Law for Conviction of ſin, ſo you muſt alſo look into your own Conſciences, and read what is there regiſtred, and compare your hearts and lives with the Law; and you ſhould call to minde the places you have lived in, the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſes you have been employed about, and the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of your lives may bring to remembrance many ſins committed long ago, with their aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. You muſt get thus a conviction of the guilt of your ſins, eſpecially if you have fallen into any groſſer ſin in your life, as adultery, drunkenneſs, theft, if you have been guilty of ſwearing, Sabbath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breaking, profaneneſs, or the like; you muſt ſee the heinouſneſs of them, and withall you muſt ſee that every ſin which you have committed is heinous, as
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:154091:22"/> it is a diſhonour to the higheſt Majeſty, who is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely more exalted above the greateſt Earthly Kings and Potentates, than they are exalted above the meaneſt Worm, or Flie; and for ſuch as you to diſhonour and affront him by ſin, is very heinous. This is the firſt thing, a Conviction of your ſins, which you muſt endeavour after.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. That you may be ſenſible of your loſt eſtate, you muſt get <hi>a conviction of the puniſhment which God hath threatned, and you have deſerved for your ſins;</hi> will the Lord put up the affronts which are offered to him by his Creatures? will he bear the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of his great and glorious Name by ſin, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out puniſhing the ſinners? No ſurely, his holineſs will not permit it, his Juſtice hath been offended, and muſt have ſatisfaction, and therefore he threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to puniſh the offenders moſt ſeverely; God threatneth temporal calamities and death, as the wages of ſin; and becauſe through patience he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beareth to puniſh many tranſgreſſions ſo remarkably in this life; and the moſt dreadfull temporal Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which he inflicteth upon any, are no wayes proportionable to the deſert of their ſins, and the demands of his infinite Juſtice; therefore he threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth eternal puniſhment in Hell; look into ſome places of Scripture, where the Lord doth denounce ſevere threatnings againſt ſinners, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 10. <hi>Curſed is every one that continueth not in all things which are written in the book of the Law to do them.</hi> Rom. 1. 18. <hi>The wrath of God is revealed from Heaven, againſt all ungodlineſs and unrighteouſneſs of men.</hi> Eph. 5. 6. <hi>Becauſe of theſe things cometh the wrath of God upon the children of diſobedience.</hi> 2 Theſſ. 1. 8, 9. <hi>Chriſt will come in flaming fire, taking vengeance
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:154091:23"/> on them which know not God, and obey not the Goſpel, who ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting deſtruction from the prefence of the Lord, and the glory of his power,</hi> Rom. 2. 6, 8, 9. <hi>God will render unto every man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his deeds, to them who are contentious and do not obey the truth, indignation and wrath, tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and anguiſh on every ſoul of man that doth evil.</hi> That you may ſee and be ſenſible of your loſt eſtate, you muſt be convinced not only in the general of the juſtice and equity that ſuch Judgements ſhould be inflicted on ſinners, becauſe God himſelf hath denounced them in his Word, who cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt toward his Creatures; and becauſe ſin hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved them, being the breach of his Law, which is holy and juſt and good; and an offence of an infinite Majeſty, whoſe Juſtice is infinite, and muſt be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with a proportionable puniſhment unto the offence: but alſo you muſt be convinced that you are ſuch ſinners; that you have committed ſuch and ſuch ſins, that you have broken the Law in ſuch a point, and ſuch a point, and in every point; that you are guilty of fornication, or drunkenneſs, or theft, or covetouſneſs, or lying, or profaneneſs; and it may be of all theſe, and more than theſe: The firſt is the conviction of the Law, the ſecond the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of the Fact, then follows the third convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which is of the State, that therefore you are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Curſe, that you are condemned, that the wrath of God hangeth over your head, and that you muſt be tormented for ſin moſt horribly and eternally in Hell: It is the conviction of the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full puniſhment of Hell which God hath threatned, and unto which you are expoſed for ſin, that will awaken you to a ſenſe of your loſt ſtate, when the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:154091:23"/> conviction is imprinted deep upon you by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; when you believe that Hell is no Fiction, but a reality, as certainly prepared for the wicked, as God is above preparing places in Heaven for his people; and you have a peep-hole (as it were) into Hell, and imagine ſomething of the torments which the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned there do, and ſhall endure for ſuch ſins as you have committed; how they roll and tumble in flames of brimſtone, how they are laſhed by an accuſing Conſcience, tormented with and by the Devil, and even conſumed by the wrath of a ſin-revenging God; how they cry, roar and howl, how they weep and wail, and gnaſh their teeth, and that this muſt be their condition for ever; and when withall you think that you are walking upon the brink of this pit, and haſtening towards the place of theſe flames, that Hell doth belong to you, that you are in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the curſed crew, ſome of whom have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy taken up their lodging in Hell, and that you are like to come thither ſhortly, that you are lyable every moment to drop into the burning Lake, then you will perceive that you are loſt and undone.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. That you may be ſenſible of your loſt eſtate, you muſt <hi>be convinced of your inſufficiency to ſatisfie Gods Juſtice for your ſins;</hi> if you could do this, you might do well enough; but this you cannot do, Gods Juſtice is infinite, and requireth infinite ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, which you being finite are inſufficient to give; what can you offer to God? thouſands of Rams, rivers of Oyl, Mines of Silver, Mountains of Gold, Rocks of Pearl, yea the whole Creation, if it ſhould offer it ſelf to be annihilated, could not make compenſation to Gods Juſtice for one ſin, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs than infinite muſt be the ſatisfaction; and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:154091:24"/> therefore this ſhould make you further ſenſible of your loſt eſtate in your ſelves.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. You muſt get a <hi>conviction of your inability to reſiſt and defend your ſelves againſt God,</hi> who hath threatned ſo ſeverely to puniſh you for ſin; as Gods Juſtice is infinite, and therefore you cannot ſatisfie it; ſo his Power is infinite, and you cannot reſiſt it; who can ſtand in his ſight when once he is angry? who can defend himſelf againſt an Omnipotent arm? If God whet his glittering Sword, and his hand take hold on vengeance, what Powers of Earth are ſtrong enough to make reſiſtance? Read how God expreſſeth himſelf concerning ſuch as ſet themſelves againſt him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27. 4. <hi>Who would ſet the bryars and thorns againſt me in battel? I would go thorow them, I would burn them together.</hi> Look upon your ſelves as briars and thorns, yea as dryed ſtubble before a conſuming fire, which hath no power to reſiſt the flame; and therefore that you are loſt and undone in your ſelves becauſe of your ſins.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. You muſt get <hi>a conviction of the impoſſibility of your fleeing from and eſcaping Gods wrath,</hi> which hath you in purſuit; whither can you go from his preſence? or whither can you flee from his anger and indignation? See <hi>Amos</hi> 9. 2, 3. <hi>Though they dig into Hell, thence ſhall mine hand take them; though they climb up into Heaven, thence will I bring them down; and though they hide themſelves in the top of</hi> Carmel, <hi>I will ſearch and take them out thence; and though they be hid from my ſight in the bottom of the Sea, thence will I command the Serpent, and he ſhall bite them.</hi> You cannot flee into any place but God will follow you; you cannot hide your ſelves in any place but God will finde you; there is as little hopes
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:154091:24"/> of eſcaping Gods Wrath, as of reſiſting his Power. See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21. 8, 9. <hi>Thine hand ſhall finde out all thine enemies,</hi> not only ſome, but all ſinners, <hi>thy right hand ſhall finde out them that hate thee: Thou ſhalt make them as a fiery. Oven in the time of thine angers the Lord ſhall ſwallow them up in his wrath, and the fire ſhall devour them.</hi> By this time ſinners, methinks you ſhould perceive your ſelves to be loſt and un-done; all refuge now fails you, there is no eſcaping for you.</p>
                        <p n="6">6. But laſtly, that you may fully know that you are in a loſt eſtate, you muſt get <hi>conviction, that as yet you have no intereſt in Chriſt, who alone can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver you from the wrath of God, which is to come upon the ungodly.</hi> Indeed Chriſt can and doth deliver his people from wrath, and the puniſhment their ſins have deſerved; but when you know that you are out of Chriſt, then you may know you are in a loſt eſtate; if you ſuppoſe that you have an intereſt in him without good grounds, you are like to be loſt irrecoverably, and not know it till it be too late; therefore you muſt know that as yet you have no intereſt in him, that all your pretenſions to him have been preſumptuous conceits; that ſo you may be loſt in your own apprehenſions. Can you think you have an intereſt in Chriſt, that never truly mourned for ſin, that never hungred after Chriſt, that have no true Faith to apply him? have you intereſt in Chriſt that have no true Love to Chriſt, and never yielded ſubjection to Chriſt? Have you intereſt in Chriſt that have no Influence from Chriſt? have you Union to Chriſt that have no Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with him? No, no, all you that are Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, and have perſiſted hitherto in a ſinfull courſe,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:154091:25"/> are ſtrangers unto Chriſt, and therefore be convinced that you are in a loſt eſtate: And O how ſhould fear and trembling poſſeſs you through the apprehenſions of the dreadfull wrath of God? how ſhould you go up and down like condemned malefactors, that are condemned to Hell, and know not how ſoon they may be dragged to execution? O what reaſon have you to lye down in terrour, and riſe up in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and feed upon terrour all the day long! Such thoughts as theſe are ſuitable to the condition of ſuch as you. <hi>It may be the next ſtep I take, I may ſtep into Hell: Alas! Alas! I am in a ſtate of damnation, and did not know it; I have been dancing about the brinks of Hell, and did not perceive it; I have been af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronting God all my daies by my ſins; now I ſee that God is highly offended with me for thoſe ſins I made light of: I am the covetous perſon whom the Lord abhorreth,</hi> Pſal. 10. 3. <hi>I am the deceiver whom he curſeth,</hi> Mal. 1. 14. <hi>I am the Adulterer whom he will judge,</hi> Heb 11. 4. <hi>I have greatly ſinned, and now I ſee God is greatly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and his anger burns like fire; he frowns, and his frowns are moſt dreadfull, and I fear he will caſt me to Hell, and make me feel the power of his anger in my everlaſting ruine; I fear I muſt dwell with devouring fire, and take up mine eternal abode with the Devil and my fellow-damned ſinners: O I fear I am damned! I am damned! O happy is the Dog and the Horſe, yea the Worm and the Toad, who ere long ſhall be anihilated; but I am curſed, and I fear that I ſhall eternally be tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented: O I am loſt, I have loſt my God, and I fear I am loſt, and ſhall be loſt for ever! O I am undone! un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done! vile and miſerable ſinner! O wo be to me that ever I was born! that ever I ſinned, and provoked God to ſuch diſpleaſure! But is there no ſpark of hope
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:154091:25"/> yet? is there no eſcaping, no reconciliation attainable? O what ſhall I do to be ſaved! I cannot ſave my ſelf, and no creature can help me; but is there no other way?</hi> Thus you muſt ſee and be ſenſible that you are loſt in your ſelves if you would be ſaved.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="direction">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Direction</hi> 2. <hi>You muſt mourn for ſin,</hi> if you would be ſaved; except ye repent, ſaith our Saviour, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13. 3. Thoſe that laugh and rejoyce now in a way of ſin, ſhall mourn and weep for it for ever to no purpoſe, <hi>Luk</hi> 6. 25. But bleſſed are they that mourn for ſin now, for they ſhall be comforted and ſaved, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 4. The ſeed time of repentance accompanied with the ſhowers of tears, will return with the harveſt of ſalvation, and ſheaves of joy and comfort, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126. 5, 6. <hi>They that ſow in tears ſhall reap in joy; he that goeth forth and weepeth, bearing precious ſeed, ſhall doubtleſs come again with rejoycing, bringing his ſheaves with him,</hi> Therefore ſee what the Apoſtle exhorteth unto, which is neceſſary to your ſalvation, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 9. <hi>Be afflicted, and mourn, and weep; let your laughter be turned into mourning, and your joy into heavineſs. Humble your ſelves in the ſight of the Lord, and he ſhall lift you up.</hi> Sinners, you have delighted your ſelves in ſin, you muſt now be afflicted for it; ſin hath been ſweet in your mouth, it muſt now be bitter to your heart: God calls you to ſalvation by his Son, but withall he calls you to weeping, and mourning, and deep humiliation in order hereunto; not that your tears can waſh off the guilt of your ſins, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can do this but the blood of Chriſt; not that God delights in your griefs and ſorrows as ſuch, but
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:154091:26"/> becauſe mourning is needful for you to prepare you for Chriſt, and Salvation by him; whilſt ſin is ſweet unto your taſte, you will roll it under your tongue, and hug it in your boſom; you will ſpare it, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will perſwade you to part with it; but when you taſte the bitterneſs of ſin in compunction and ſorrow for it, then you will ſpit it out; when you perceive the gall and the worm wood, then your mouth will be put out of relliſh, then you will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire no longer to ſuck at the breaſt of ſin; whilſt you are inſenſible of ſin, you will be inſenſible of your need of a Saviour: None but ſick perſons do prize and ſend for the Phyſitian, and none but ſuch as are ſick of ſin, and groan and mourn under the burden of this ſickneſs, do prize a Chriſt who is the ſoul-Phyſician, <hi>Matth.</hi> 9. 12. Were you made ſenſible of ſin indeed, you would eagerly enquire after Chriſt, and greedily hearken unto the glad tydings of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which he hath purchaſed; what ſhall I do to get an intereſt in Chriſt? where is he to be found? how is he to be received? what are his terms? what are his commands? do any thing, part with any thing, you would not then think much to lay down your ſelves, and all that you have at his feet, ſo you might have him; none but Chriſt, none but Chriſt would you then deſire; and if you might have all the world without him, you would not be contented. Sinners, would you be ſaved by Chriſt, get your hearts af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with godly ſorrow for ſin, and that you may mourn deeply and kindly, you muſt get not only a conviction of the guilt of ſin, and the puniſhment which is due for it, which you cannot eſcape; but you muſt look further into the nature of ſin, and get a ſight and ſenſe of the evil of ſin; you muſt look
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:154091:26"/> not only to the conſequential evil of ſin, but alſo to the intrinſecal evil of ſin; not only to the Hell which is like to follow upon it, but alſo to that Hell which there is in it; look to the evil of ſin not only as it is like to burn you, but as it hath blackt and ſmutted you; as it hath depraved and deformed your ſouls, which are of heavenly original, as it hath degraded and debaſed you, polluted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed you. But chiefly look upon the evil of ſin as it reflecteth diſhonour upon God, upon God that is ſo holy and glorious, and that is ſo good and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, as it diſpleaſeth that God that made you, that hath exerciſed ſo much patience towards you, when he could ſo eaſily have cut you off in the act of ſin, and appointed you your place and portion amongſt the damned in Hell long ago; and that hath more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over been ſo bountiful to you, though ſinners and his enemies, that he hath maintained you at his coſt and charges all your daies; but eſpecially ſee the evil of ſin, as it offendeth that God who is ready to be reconciled, and hath made ſuch proviſion for recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, which you could never have thought of, namely, through the death and mediation of his Son, whom he hath given for you, and proffers to give to you; and in him doth treat with you, and by us Miniſters doth ſend intreaties to you, that you would accept of this reconciliation, lay down your wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, and be reconciled unto him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 20. Break, break ye rocky hearts at this, what is God willing indeed to put up ſuch high affronts? and to forgive ſuch great ſins? and doth he ſtoop to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat and beſeech ſuch mean creatures, and wretched ſinners as you to be reconciled? O be filled with aſtoniſhment and admiration, and go caſt your
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:154091:27"/> ſelves down at his feet with ſelf-loathing and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency at the hideous nature, and monſtrous ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and baſeneſs of your ſins! let your hearts melt within you like Wax, or Snow, when the Sun ſhineth upon it with heat and brightneſs; let your eyes drop down tears, as the morning doth drop dew upon the flowers: <hi>What! have I affronted ſuch greatneſs? dared ſuch power? trampled upon ſuch patience? and abuſed ſuch goodneſs too? and after all doth God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech me to be reconciled? was it ſuch a God whom I offended? vile wreth! O that I had never committed ſuch ſins! O that I had never been drunk, or unclean, or profane! O that I had never ſworn, nor lyed, nor ſtoln, nor offended God in any of my actions! It repents me, it grieves me at the very heart that I have ſinned, and that I can grieve no more for it.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="direction">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Direction</hi> 3. <hi>You muſt turn from ſin,</hi> if you would be ſaved; ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7. 11, 12, 13. <hi>God is angry with the wicked every day; if he turn not, he will whet his ſword; he hath bent his bow, and made it ready; he hath prepared for him the inſtruments of death.</hi> And God threatneth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88. 21. that he will <hi>wound the head of his enemies, and the hairy ſcalp of ſuch as go on ſtill in their treſpaſſes:</hi> Therefore men muſt turn from all their tranſgreſſions, otherwiſe iniquity will be their ruine, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. 30. They muſt caſt away their ſins as a menſtruous cloth, ſaying unto them, get ye hence, if they would be received into favour, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30. 22. They muſt not only confeſs their ſins, but alſo forſake them, if they would find mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28. 13. The wicked muſt forſake his way, and the unrighteous man his thoughts, and turn to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:154091:27"/> the Lord, and then he ſhall have pardoning mercy abundantly, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. 7. When men ceaſe to do evil, and learn to do well, then, though their ſins have been as ſcarlet, they ſhall be white as ſnow; though they be red like crimſon, they ſhall be like wooll, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 16, 17, 18. Sinners, turn from your evil waies, you have done iniquity, do ſo no more; you have gone on hitherto in a way of ſin, proceed no further, it is the way to Hell, turn out of it: Let him that hath ſtoln, ſteal no more; and him that hath been filthy, be filthy no more; and him that hath been unjuſt, be unjuſt no more: Drunkards, forbear your drinking; ſwearers, refrain ſwearing; lyars, teach your tongues to ſpeak truth: Break off your courſe of ſin; turn from all groſs ſins as to the practice, and turn from all ſins as to the affection.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="direction">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Direction</hi> 4. <hi>You muſt believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> if you would be ſaved: This is the direction which <hi>Paul</hi> gave to the Jaylor, when under con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of ſin he came in to him and cryed, <hi>What ſhall I do to be ſaved?</hi> he ſaith to him, <hi>Believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt and thou ſhalt be ſaved, Act.</hi> 16. 30, 31. So in <hi>Peter</hi>'s Sermon, <hi>Act.</hi> 10. 43. <hi>To him gave all the Prophets witneſs, that through his Name, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever believeth in him ſhould receive remiſſion of ſins.</hi> There is no Saviour but by Chriſt; and there is no ſalvation by Chriſt but by faith, and therefore we are ſaid to be ſaved through faith, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 8. As faith is the inſtrument to apply the merits and righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt. Let me then exhort you to get faith, which is abſolutely neceſſary unto ſalvation: Get faith of the right kind; there is a general, common, hiſtorical, temporary, hypocritical, dead
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:154091:28"/> and ineffectual faith; but do you labour after a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial, lively, unfeigned, effectual, juſtifying and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving faith; and that you may not be miſtaken in this great point on which your ſalvation doth depend, I ſhall deſcribe that faith which is of the right kind, and will certainly ſave you if you obtain it.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Faith is a grace wrought in the heart by the Spirit of God, whereby a poor ſinner being made ſenſible of the guilt and power of his ſins, and the utter inſufficiency of himſelf, or any creature in the world, to give him any help or ſuccour; and having in the Goſpel a diſcovery and proffer made unto him of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as an all ſufficient, moſt merciful and faithful Advocate and Saviour, doth go quite out of himſelf, and accept, lay hold, rely, and reſt upon him, and him alone, for pardon, and grace, and everlaſting happineſs.</hi> Or more briefly thus, <hi>Faith is a grace of God whereby the humbled ſinner doth accept and rely upon Chriſt alone for ſalvation, as he is held forth in the Promiſes of the Goſpel.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>If you would attain this grace of Faith, take theſe Directions.</p>
                        <div n="1" type="direction">
                           <p>1. You muſt be fully perſwaded that the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures which reveal Chriſt, are indeed the word of God; this is the foundation of all faith, therefore I ſhall briefly ſuggeſt ſome Arguments to prove the divine Authority of the Scriptures: As 1. Becauſe of that majeſty, purity, holineſs, heavenlineſs which doth appear in the Scriptures beyond all other writings. 2. Becauſe of the deſign and drift of the Scriptures to debaſe man, and exalt God and his glory above all. 3. Becauſe of the admirable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texture, and contrivance, and ſweet harmony of the Scriptures in all the parts thereof, though writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by ſo many ſeveral men in ſeveral ages and places,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:154091:28"/> which ſheweth that they were all acted by the ſame Spirit of God. 4. Becauſe of the wonderfull work of mans Redemption there ſet forth at firſt more dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, afterwards more clearly, which no mortal brain could have invented, much leſs could any created power have effected. 5. Becauſe of the great power which this word hath to convince, convert, and comfort. 6. Becauſe of the confirmation of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures by miracles. 7. Becauſe of the acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Scriptures to be Gods Word in all ages. 8. Becauſe of the many millions of Martyrs, who have ſealed the Truths of the word with their blood. 9. Becauſe of the witneſs of the Spirit in and with the word, which doth bear teſtimony to the hearts of Gods people, that the Scriptures are his Word, and were indited by his Spirit. Whence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that the Scriptures are true, becauſe God, the Author of them, is true, and cannot lye; and whatever is there revealed, is as certain as thoſe things which are moſt demonſtrable to ſenſe or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: This is the firſt ſtep to your believing in Chriſt who is made known in the Scriptures, to believe that the Scriptures are Gods Word.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="direction">
                           <p>2. If you would attain a ſaving faith in Chriſt, you muſt be convinced and fully perſwaded of your loſt eſtate without Chriſt, and your abſolute need of him, of which before.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="3" type="direction">
                           <p>3. You muſt be perſwaded, that it is not in your own power to believe, that it is not of your ſelves, but is the gift of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 8. and therefore muſt apply your ſelves to God, that he would not only give you his Son, but alſo give you the hand of faith to lay hold on him, that he would work in you this grace of faith by his Spirit.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="4" type="direction">
                           <pb n="52" facs="tcp:154091:29"/>
                           <p>4. You muſt conſider thoſe Arguments of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture which encourage faith: As for inſtance, I ſhall mention four heads of Arguments for faith, from the conſideration 1. Of God. 2. Of the Promiſes. 3. Of Chriſt. 4. Of the Saints.</p>
                           <p n="1">1. From the conſideration of God, who hath given his Son to ſave ſinners; it is an encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to faith, to conſider, 1. That God is mercifull, and therefore willing to pardon and ſave, otherwiſe he would not have ſent his Son; he doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the death of ſinners, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. 23. but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth to ſhew mercy; ſee <hi>Micah</hi> 7. 18, 19. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. 6, 7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. 8, 9, &amp;c. 2. That God is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in his Promiſes of ſalvation, which he hath made through his Son in his Covenant of Grace: God needed not have made the Covenant, nor promiſed mercy to any ſinners; but having made the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, he is engaged to make it good. 3. That it is for his glory to ſave ſinners through his Son, the glory of his free grace, yea and juſtice too, which hath been fully ſatisfied by Chriſts death.</p>
                           <p n="2">2. You have encouraging Arguments for faith, from the conſideration of the Promiſes, which are, 1. Large, made to all ſorts of perſons, and all ſorts of ſinners, none are excluded. 2. Full, they extend to all ſorts of ſins, though never ſo many and great, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. 7. 3. Free, nothing is required on your part but accepting. 4. Sure, being the Promiſes of God in Chriſt.</p>
                           <p n="3">3. You have encouragement to believe in Chriſt for ſalvation, from the conſideration of Chriſt, the proper object of faith: 1. The quality of his perſon who is God and man in one perſon, that he might reconcile man unto God. 2. The merit of his
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:154091:29"/> ſufferings, which (as hath been ſhown) was of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite value, and ſufficient for the redemption of men. 3. His alſufficient power to ſave thoſe that come to him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 25. 4. His mercy and faithfulneſs to make reconciliation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 17. 5. His intereſt with the Father. 6. His continual interceſſion at the right hand of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 25.</p>
                           <p n="4">4. You have encouragement to believe in Chriſt for ſalvation, from the conſideration of the Saints, the experience which they have had of ſalvation by Chriſt, ſome of whom have been as vile ſinners as you: You have as good grounds to come unto Chriſt, and believe in him for ſalvation, as the moſt holy men alive before converſion.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="5" type="direction">
                           <p>5. If you would attain this grace of faith in Jeſus Chriſt, you muſt labour to act it, looking up to God for help herein; endeavour to caſt and roll your ſelves upon Chriſt, to apply Chriſt and his merits, and to rely upon him and his righteouſneſs: It is in your endeavour that God doth work; and here you muſt endeavour again and again againſt all oppoſition which you find from the Devil and your own evil heart of unbelief, which will be ready to carry you away from Chriſt. So much for the 4th. Direction.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="direction">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Direction</hi> 5. <hi>You muſt get a new Nature,</hi> if you would be ſaved: You muſt be made partakers of the Divine Nature, if you would be made partakers of this ſalvation: You have brought unholy and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure natures into the world with you, which muſt be changed and renewed after the Image of God, in knowledge, righteouſneſs, and true holineſs, before you can be in a ſtate of ſalvation, and ſee the Kingdom
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:154091:30"/> of God: This new nature, which is abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary unto ſalvation, is begun in the work of rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and carried on in the work of ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: In regeneration the work of grace is begun, the habits of grace are infuſed; a new principle of ſpiritual life is put into the ſoul; and ſin (which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore lived, and had dominion over the man, imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all his members as inſtruments of unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to make proviſion for the ſatisfaction of its af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and luſts) doth receive its deaths wound, and loſeth its force and reigning power: In ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, the work of grace is carried on, the habits of grace are ſtrengthned and encreaſed; the new man doth grow, and the old man doth decline and decay; there is a vivification or quickning more and more of grace, by the influence of the Word and Spirit, and a mortification or ſubduing more and more of remaining iniquity. What our Saviour tells <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> Joh. 3. 3. <hi>Except a man be born again, he cannot ſee the Kingdom of God:</hi> I may tell you, that unleſs ye be born again, unleſs ye be regenerated, ye cannot be ſaved, no poſſibility of entring into the Kingdom of Heaven, without you get this new na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: A man muſt be born the firſt time, before he can poſſeſs a temporal inheritance; and a man muſt be born again, before he can poſſeſs the eternal inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: You muſt be children, before you can be heirs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 17. children not only by adoption, but alſo by regeneration: Ye muſt be Saints, before meet to be partakers of the inheritance of the Saints in light, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 12. You muſt have the new nature, before you can enter into the New <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> You muſt be made like to God in holineſs, before you can be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to live with God in the place of everlaſting
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:154091:30"/> happineſs; God doth ſuffer the wicked that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean and unholy, to live before him in the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of the Earth; but he will not permit any except ſuch as are ſanctified to live with him in the Palace of Heaven. O then labour after a work of Grace upon your hearts; be perſwaded of the worth of Grace, that it is a rare and precious Jewel, that the leaſt meaſure of Grace is of more worth than ten thouſand Worlds; be ſenſible of your want of it, that naturally you are without it, that it doth not grow in Natures Garden, that you have no good Nature in you before God, till your Nature is renewed; be ready to receive the ſeed of Grace, which drops down from above whileſt People are attending upon Gods Ordinances; be ready to hearken and yield to the Spirits motions, whereby this work of Grace is effected: And having the work begun, O cheriſh the Grace you have got, and as new-born Babes deſire the ſincere milk of the Word, that ye may grow thereby; and labour to cleanſe your ſelves from all filthineſs of Fleſh and Spirit, that ye may perfect holineſs in the fear of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 1.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="direction">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Direction</hi> 6. <hi>You muſt lead a new Life,</hi> if you would be ſaved; ſee what kind of Life the grace of God which bringeth ſalvation doth require and teach, namely, <hi>to deny ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly, righteouſly and godly in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world,</hi> Tit. 2. 11, 12. You muſt deny ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and worldly luſts, you muſt put off concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the former converſation the old man which is corrupt according to deceitfull luſts, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 22.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:154091:31"/> and not faſhion your ſelves according to the former luſts, in your ignorance and unregeneracy, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 14. not running with others unto the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of riot, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 4. not walking according to the courſe of a profane and ungodly world, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 2. but ſaving your ſelves from an untoward ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 40. as he that hath called you is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo you muſt be holy in all manner of converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 15. you muſt live <hi>ſoberly, righteouſly,</hi> and <hi>godly</hi> in this preſent world; <hi>ſoberly</hi> in regard of your ſelves; <hi>righteouſly</hi> in regard of others; and <hi>godly</hi> in regard of the Lord.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. <hi>Soberly,</hi> in regard of your ſelves; which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes, 1. Temperance in eating and drinking, you muſt take heed of Gluttony and Drunkenneſs: 2. Chaſtity, you muſt take heed of Adultery and Uncleanneſs, in thought, ſpeech, look, and act. 3. Moderation, you muſt be ſober in your deſires after theſe earthly things, and take heed of inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate affection to any thing.</p>
                        <p n="2">2 You muſt live <hi>Righteouſly</hi> in regard of others: You muſt give to every one their due, and do to others as you reaſonably can deſire that they ſhould do unto you; you muſt take heed of unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs either in regard of Commutative Juſtice in your buying and ſelling, borrowing and lending; and in regard of Diſtributative Juſtice in diſpenſing of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and puniſhments; you muſt beware of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing, afflicting, injuring any, of going beyond or defrauding any, of withholding dues, keeping back wages from thoſe that have done you ſervice, knowing that if they cannot, God will be the aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of all ſuch.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. You muſt live <hi>godly</hi> in regard of the Lord;
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:154091:31"/> you muſt eſpecially ſhew your New Life in the immediate Worſhip of the Lord, and that publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his Houſe, privately in your Families, ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in your Cloſets; you muſt worſhip God in the Ordinances of his own appointment; and this you muſt do with reverence, having an awe and dread of God upon your ſpirits, with whom you have more immediately to do; with ſincerity, having a ſincere reſpect to Gods glory therein, and that you might be accepted by him, and meet with him; with vigilancy watching the fitteſt time in regard of the thing, and the temper of your Bodies and Souls, and the breathings of Gods Spirit; with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, ſenſible of your ſinfulneſs, unworthineſs, weakneſs, emptineſs, needineſs; with diligence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to prepare your hearts, and in Ordinances to engage them, and reſiſt the Devil and the contrary workings of the fleſh; with frequency, laying hold on all the opportunities as you can, without neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting other buſineſſes, which for that time you may be more neceſſarily called unto; with ſerven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, getting your hearts if you can raiſed and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, labouring that they may burn within you with love to God; with delight and complacency in God, and above all with Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, through whom alone it is that you can have ſtrength to perform duties, and that you can have any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance in them by the Father.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="direction">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Direction</hi> 7. <hi>You muſt reſolve upon ſufferings for Chriſt, if called,</hi> if you would be ſaved; you muſt bear the Croſs, if you would wear the Crown, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring that if the Croſs be weighty it will work
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:154091:32"/> for you a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 17. you muſt reckon upon ſufferings for Chriſt before hand, and reſolve that you will ſtick to him and his wayes, though you ſhould loſe eſteem by it, and become the Drunkards Song, and be reproached amongſt men; though you loſe liberty by it, and be thruſt into Priſon; though you ſhould loſe Eſtate by it, and be brought to pinch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing want; though you ſhould loſe Friends by it, and have none to ſtand by you; though you ſhould loſe Life by it, and be cut off in the midſt of your years; otherwiſe you cannot be Chriſts Diſciples indeed, and obtain this ſalvation which he hath purchaſed. See the terms which our Saviour pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. 26, 27. <hi>If any man come unto me, and hate not his Father and Mother, and Wife and Children, and Brethren and Siſters, yea and his own life, he cannot be my Diſciple.</hi> This we are to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that a man muſt chooſe to diſpleaſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Mother, Wife, Children, the neareſt and deareſt Relations, and part with any thing in the world, yea with Life it ſelf, rather than to diſpleaſe and part with Jeſus Chriſt; and that we muſt reſolve to bear the Croſs, whatever it be that God hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted for us, otherwiſe we do not accept of Chriſt upon Goſpel-terms; you muſt reſolve to be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the <hi>affliction</hi> of the Goſpel, if you would obtain the <hi>ſalvation</hi> of the Goſpel; you muſt reſolve to ſuffer with Chriſt, and for his ſake when called, if you would reign and be glorified together with him. Whatever profeſſion you make of Chriſt and his wayes in time of peace and proſperity, when the Sun of perſecution doth ariſe upon you with burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heat, you will wither and fall away, and turn
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:154091:32"/> fearfull Apoſtates, and then your laſt eſtate will be worſe than your firſt; and as your ſin will be greater here, ſo your puniſhment will be more dreadfull hereafter in Hell, where you will confeſs that the light ſufferings which you have declined for Chriſts ſake here, are not worthy to be compared with the far more exceeding and eternal weight of wrath which you muſt endure for your Apoſtacy unto all eternity.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="direction">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Direct.</hi> 8. <hi>You muſt ſtudy and apply the Promiſes of the Covenant of grace,</hi> if you would be ſaved; without the Covenant of grace there had been no poſſible ſalvation for any of the fallen Children of Men; the Covenant of Works which God made with Man at the firſt, being broken by ſin, it doth condemn all that are under it; it is by vertue of the Covenant of Grace that any are brought into a ſtate of ſalvation; therefore ſtudy and apply the Promiſes of this Covenant: Now you muſt know that all the Promiſes of the Goſpel, which are ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered up and down the Scripture do belong unto this Covenant; but I ſhall ſpread before you thoſe few more general Promiſes which the Apoſtle doth make mention of, where he treats of the New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. 10, 11, 12. <hi>For this is the Covenant that I will make with the houſe of Iſrael after thoſe dayes, ſaith the Lord, I will put my Lawes into their minde, and write them in their hearts, and I will be to them a God, and they ſhall be to me a People; and they ſhall not teach every man his Neighbour, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man his Brother, ſaying know the Lord, for they ſhall all know me from the leaſt to the greateſt; for
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:154091:33"/> I will be mercifull unto their unrighteouſneſs, and their ſins and iniquities will I remember no more.</hi> Here are Four great Promiſes which the Lord hath made to his People, which I ſhall explain (though not in the order of the Text) that you may the better underſtand and apply them.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. God promiſeth that <hi>he will be to them a God, and they ſhall be to him a People;</hi> this includes all the reſt: It is a full and ſweet promiſe that God will be our God, it hath a great deal more in it, than we can conceive; we may look and look again, and though our Faith have never ſo piercing an eye, never ſo large and deep reach, yet we cannot look to the bottom, and fathom the depth of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; we may ſuck and ſuck again at this breaſt, and though we draw never ſo hard, we can never draw forth all the ſweetneſs that is in this Promiſe. To have God to be our God, it is very great, it is very ſweet: Indeed God is the God of all his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, yea of his enemies, and the vileſt ſinners; but to be our God in this place ſounds and ſignifieth more than that which is common to all; it ſpeaketh a peculiar relation, a ſpecial intereſt and propriety in God; in this promiſe God doth make over him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and all that he hath to us, ſo far as we are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of receiving; he giveth himſelf to be our portion, he engageth his Power, Wiſdom, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Mercy, Love, and all his Attributes to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed for our good, he promiſeth to be our God here, and to be our God for ever; it ſignifieth that he will be our Father to love and cheriſh us, to preſerve, and provide for us whileſt we live, and to take our Souls to himſelf when we dye, and to raiſe up our bodies at the laſt day, and make both
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:154091:33"/> perfectly glorious and happy in Heaven, when time ſhall be no more. He promiſeth alſo that <hi>we ſhall be his People;</hi> we cannot make our ſelves ſo, but he promiſeth that he will make us ſo; he will make us his Children, he will adopt us, he will regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate us, give us the title, and give us the diſpoſition of Children; all this and much more is contained in this Promiſe, <hi>That God will be our God, and we ſhall be his People,</hi> even the whole work of our ſalvation from our effectual Calling unto our eternal Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. A ſecond great Promiſe of the Covenant of Grace is, <hi>That God will be mercifull unto our unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and that he will remember no more our ſins and iniquities;</hi> it is a promiſe of mercy in the free pardon and forgiveneſs of all our ſins, this is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great and precious promiſe, without which there were no acceſs for us unto God, no attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eternal happineſs, no eſcaping eternal miſery, guilt would ſhut us out of Heaven, and ſink us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hell without a pardon. This Promiſe is of vaſt extent, it reacheth to all ſort of ſins, Unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Sins, Iniquities; no ſin is too great for God to pardon, if the ſinner doth believe.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. A third Promiſe of the Covenant of Grace is, that <hi>God will give us the knowledge of himſelf;</hi> they <hi>ſhall not teach every man his Neighbour, and every man his Brother, ſaying, Know the Lord, for they ſhall all know me from the leaſt to the greateſt;</hi> they ſhall not teach one another the knowledge of God, that is, they cannot, or they ſhall not be able to do it; they may and ought to teach one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtrumentally; it is the duty of ſome to teach, and the duty of others, and they have need, to learn,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:154091:34"/> but they ſhall not be able to teach effectually; they may give inſtructions to one another concerning God and his wayes; but they cannot give light; they may ſet the light before them, but they cannot ſet up the light in them; they may open Truths, but they cannot open the Underſtanding; this is the work of God only to do, and this he hath undertaken by Promiſe to do, <hi>they ſhall all know me,</hi> they ſhall be taught of God by his Spirit the knowledge of himſelf; he teacheth by men inſtrumentally, but he will teach us by his Spirit effectually.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. A fourth Promiſe of the Covenant of Grace, is, that <hi>God will put his laws into our hearts, and write them in our minds:</hi> the Law was written be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore on Tables of Stone, but here he promiſeth to write them on fleſhly Tables of the heart; which is done not with Pen and Ink, but by the Spirit of the living God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 3. this Promiſe is very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive, it includes not only the giving of a ſpiritual diſcovery of the minde and will of God, but alſo the giving of ſpiritual diſpoſitions, affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſtrength to perform it; and by conſequence the removal of indiſpoſitions, the purging out of corruptions, the mortifying of luſt, the taking away the heart of ſtone, and giving a heart of fleſh, the giving a new heart, the putting the Spirit within us, and cauſing us to walk in his Statutes, and to keep his Judgements and do them, as this Promiſe is branched forth, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 25, 26, 27.</p>
                        <p>Theſe in brief are the chief Promiſes of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, labour to underſtand them, and apply them that you may be ſaved.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="direction">
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:154091:34"/>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Direct.</hi> 9. <hi>You muſt give up your ſelves in Covenant to God,</hi> if you would be ſaved; God hath put his hand and ſeal to the Covenant which he hath made through his Son with you, and you ſhould put your hand to the Covenant and engage your ſelves unto the Lord; you were dedicated to the Lord by your Parents when you were baptized, then you underſtood not what was done; now you are arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to years of underſtanding, you ſhould make it your own act, and dedicate your ſelves to the Lord: and the more ſolemnly you enter into Covenant with God, the more ſtrong Obligation it may be upon you to walk cloſely with God all your dayes: Some have directed to do it under hand-writing, ſubſcribing the name, and ſome have put words into your mouths, which you may do it, in if you are not ſo well able to expreſs the terms your ſelves; you have this done in Mr. <hi>Guthry</hi> and Mr. <hi>Allen</hi>'s books, if thoſe Books be not at hand, I ſhall ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you this Platform, which you may make uſe of in entring ſolemnly into Covenant with God.</p>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="covenant">
                           <body>
                              <p>I <hi>A. B.</hi> do acknowledge my ſelf to be the Creature and Subject of the great and glorious Majeſty of Heaven and Earth, in whom I live, move, and have my being, and from whom I receive every good thing which I receive; and therefore am obliged to conform my minde, will and affections, to order my words, wayes and whole converſation according to his moſt wiſe and good, moſt righteous and reaſonable Laws: Beſides which natural Obligation, however born in ſin, and thereby diſenabled, yet being born in the Church, and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:154091:35"/> Baptized in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, and by my Parents dedicated unto God when I was an Infant; I am further obliged by Covenant to be the ſervant of the Lord. But having proved a Rebel and Traytor againſt the Higheſt Majeſty, breaking his Laws, and Covenant-ties which have been upon me, ſpending years of my life in a ſtate of ſtrangeneſs and enmity to God, in the ſervice of the Devil and my own Luſts, I do now ſolemnly renew my Covenant with God, that the breach may be made up which ſin hath made between God and my Soul.</p>
                              <p>Being in the Firſt place convinced of the guilt of my ſins, whereby I have affronted and offended the higheſt Majeſty, whoſe Juſtice muſt be ſatisfied; and withall convinced of my own utter inability to make the leaſt ſatisfaction either by doing or ſuffering, and that my Righteouſneſſes are as filthy rags, and therefore alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether inſufficient to procure for me the pardon of ſin, the favour of God, and the peace of Conſcience; as alſo fully perſwaded that no meer Creature is able to give unto me any help and relief in this caſe. And being informed by the Word of God what the Lord Jeſus is, hath done, and ſuffered for poor ſinners, That there is no Name under Heaven given amongſt men whereby we can be ſaved, but only the Name of Jeſus Chriſt; that he is able to ſave all them unto the uttermoſt that come unto God by him, ſeeing be ever liveth to make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for them; that he is a mercifull and faithfull High-prieſt in things pertaining to God, to make Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation for the ſins of the People; that whoſoever cometh unto him, he will in no wiſe caſt out: and finding a Promiſe in the Covenant of Grace that God will be mercifull unto our unrighteouſneſs, and that our ſins and iniquities he will remember no more; which
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:154091:35"/> Covenant is of full force through the death of Chriſt the Teſtator thereof: and having Chriſt ſet forth to be a propitiation through Faith in his blood, and his Righteouſneſs declared for the remiſſion of ſins which are paſt through the forbearance of God; and this Chriſt freely tendered unto me, and being invited earneſtly, yea entreated that I would be reconciled unto God through him; and by the Spirit being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of the truth of theſe things, and hereby encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to apply my ſelf unto Chriſt, and the Promiſes through him unto my ſelf: I do now (grieving that I have offended God, groaning under the burden of ſin, renouncing all my own righteouſneſs, hungring after the Lord Jeſus Chriſt and his righteouſneſs) upon the bended knees of my ſoul come unto him, and caſt my ſelf wholly upon him; I chooſe him for my only Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to plead my cauſe in the Court of Heaven, to procure for me Pardon and Reconciliation, that being juſtified by Faith, I may have peace with God through my dear Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                              <p>Next, repenting from the bottom of my heart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> of my ſins, grieving that I have ſuch a ſinfull Nature, ſuch a deceitfull heart, that I have ſo adulterated my affections, and gone a whoring from God to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that I have ſo indulged my fleſh, and ſatisfied its irregular deſires, that I have given ear to the Devil, and complyed as I have done with his tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: I now renounce all allegiance and ſervice to the World, to the Fleſh, and to the Devil, theſe enemies of the Lord, and of my peace, which warr againſt my Maſter, and againſt my own ſoul; cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting and promiſing never to give away my heart any more from the Lord unto any perſon or thing in the World; to refuſe the World for my portion and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:154091:36"/> chief happineſs; to deny my fleſh i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>s ſinfull deſires and demands; to reſiſt the Devil and his Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; not to live and allow my ſelf in any known ſin, and to make uſe of all the known means which the Lord hath preſcribed for the crucifying of the World, for the mortifying and utter extirpation of ſin, for the reſiſting and overcoming the Devil. And being perſwaded of the power and intereſt, the ſubtilty and deceitfulneſs of theſe enemies, and withall ſenſible of my own imprudence, folly, weakneſs and inconſtancy, I humbly and earneſtly implore and beſeech the higheſt Majeſty, who is infinite in wiſdom, power, and goodneſs, that he would give me counſel and diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the uſe and management of all means and helps that I may not neglect any, nor through ſloth and imprudence ſuffer a leſſer duty to juſtle out a greater, that he would give me courage, ſtrength and conſtancy in the maintaining my ſpiritual warfare againſt theſe my ſpiritual enemies unto my lifes end. And if ever I ſhould fall through unwatchfulneſs and weakneſs, (which the Lord grant I may never do) I do promiſe in the ſtrength of the Lord to ariſe again by Faith and Repentance. And becauſe of the Body of ſin within me, and remaining corruptions, I ſhall be ſubject (during my abode here) unto daily failings and infirmities; I do promiſe to pray, watch and ſtrive againſt them, beſeeching the Lord to ſtrengthen me herein, and grant that my ſinful infirmities may be leſſe every day than other; in the mean time looking upon thoſe diſallowed miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages contrary to the ſettled bent and reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my heart, as inſufficient to make my Covenant void.</p>
                              <pb n="67" facs="tcp:154091:36"/>
                              <p>Furthermore, being convinced of the vanity, empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and utter inſufficiency of any or all the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the World, to make me happy, had I the moſt deſireable enjoyment of them; and having a diſcovery of the infinitely bleſſed God made unto me in his Works, chiefly in his Word, as being the chief good of man, and withall a Promiſe in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace that he will be our God, yea our Father through Chriſt, and that we ſhall be his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, his Sons and Daughters: I do here with deep veneration of Soul, and chief eſtimation of minde, chooſe the thrice Bleſſed Jehovah for my Portion and chief good, beyond all perſons and things in this World; and do avouch him this day to be my God. I humbly accept of the relation of a Servant and a Son, or Daughter, which he hath called me unto. I put my ſelf under his wing, and commit my ſelf to his care and Tuition; and henceforth ſhall be bold through my deareſt Lord to call him, and look upon him to be my God and Father; and humbly ſhall expect from him Protection and Proviſion in his way and work, Correction, Audience of Prayer, and the fulfilling of all thoſe Promiſes unto me, which he hath made unto his Children.</p>
                              <p>Moreover, being perſwaded that none can come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Father, but by the Son; nor ſhare in any ſpiritual priviledge, but through Chriſts death and interceſſion, and being perſwaded of the infinite ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of Chriſts perſon, the greatneſs of his love and affection unto the children of men, as alſo of his infinite deſireableneſs in regard of thoſe offices, and relations which he hath vouchſafed to take upon him, and enter into for the good of his people: I do avouch the Lord Jeſus Chriſt to be my only Saviour, and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:154091:37"/> chooſe him in all his Offices and Relations. I chooſe Chriſt to be my High-Prieſt, to intercede, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure for me daily pardon, acceſs unto God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of my perſon and ſervice, audience of my prayers, and ſupply of all my wants. I chooſe Chriſt to be my Prophet, to teach me by his Word and Spirit the will of the Father. I chooſe Chriſt to be my King to rule and govern me, to command my whole man into the obedience of himſelf. I chooſe Chriſt to be my Captain, to go before me, and to tread down my ſpiritual enemies under my feet. I chooſe Chriſt to be my Friend and Brother, to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and adviſe me, to ſtand by me in all the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties and ſtraights of my life. I chooſe Chriſt to be my Husband and beloved, humbly accepting of this near and ſweet Relation which he calleth me unto. I joyn and eſpouſe my ſelf unto the Lord Jeſus; and do promiſe to be for him only, and with full pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of heart to cleave unto him, to love, honour and ſerve him, never to deny nor leave him whatever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches and diſtreſses I may meet withall for his ſake; though Perſecution ſhould ariſe, and that even unto death, I do promiſe to own his Name, and Cauſe, and Truths, and Wayes, ſo long as I have breath in my Body: But knowing that I am utterly inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to do any of theſe things in my own ſtrength, therefore upon the knees of my Soul, I earneſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech that I may have ſtrength for all theſe from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alone.</p>
                              <p>Further, becauſe God my Father is inviſible to the eye of ſenſe, and incomprehenſible by the graſp of Reaſon; and becauſe my deareſt Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who alone hath declared him, in regard of his bodily preſence is now in Heaven, abſent from his people;
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:154091:37"/> and becauſe whatever ſpiritual light or life, grace comfort, or ſpiritual communion with the Father, and with his Son, is vouchſafed unto the people of God, it is by the Holy Spirit, who is appointed by Office hereunto, and graciouſly promiſed unto them in the Word: Therefore I avouch and chooſe the Holy Ghoſt to be my Teacher and Guide, to be my Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier and Comforter, to help my infirmities in duties; to ſtrengthen me with might in my inner man againſt ſin and Satans Temptations; to cleanſe me from all filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit; to heal me of all my ſpiritual diſtempers; to revive me under all my faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; to ſupply me with all Graces as to kinde and meaſure, as ſhall be needfull for me in my place and work; to teſtifie Gods love to my Soul; to give me earneſts of Glory, and to ſeal me up unto the day of Redemption: And O that I might have the preſence and abode of the Spirit of God with me, and never grieve, quench, reſiſt, and drive away the Spirit any more!</p>
                              <p>Alſo, becauſe the Holy Scriptures are the Word of God, endited by the Holy Ghoſt, the Epiſtle of Jeſus Chriſt, wherein he hath given notice of his love and will; becauſe they are the only ſufficient, and in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a perfect Rule for Faith and a holy Life, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                                    <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                 </gap> fully do declare the way and means unto ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting happineſs: Therefore I chooſe the Word of God to be the Rule of my Faith and Life; and the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God therein preſcribed to be the means of my acquaintance and converſe with my God ſo far as I am capable of, and he ſhall vouchſafe; and to be the means alſo of preparing of me for the full and perfect enjoyment of him beyond my preſent capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city.</p>
                              <pb n="70" facs="tcp:154091:38"/>
                              <p>And, becauſe the Ordinances are but dark glaſſes to ſee the Lord in; becauſe ignorance and unbelief do exceedingly vail God from mine eyes, fleſh and corruption do damp my love to God, and my ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Joy in him, and interrupt my communion with him; becauſe of the ſins, ſorrows, temptations, and afflictions which I cannot be wholly free from, and therefore cannot be perfectly happy here in this World; and having life and immortality brought to light by the Goſpel; a diſcovery and promiſe of eternal Life made unto me in the Word, and withall a command of my Lord, to lay up my Treaſure in Heaven: Therefore I chooſe Heaven for my Treaſure and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, for ever to live there in the company of all the holy Angels and Saints, in the bleſſed ſight, love, and enjoyment of the infinitely bleſſed God, to ſee and ſhare in the glory of my Deareſt Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, whither I hope my Soul ſhall be tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Angels, ſo ſoon as it is ſeparated from my Body; and that my vile Body, when awakened and raiſed in the Morning of Chriſts coming, ſhall be faſhioned like unto Chriſts moſt beautifull and glorious Body, and both inherit the Kingdom prepared and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed by my Father.</p>
                              <p>Laſtly, being perſwaded of my Duty, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by Gods promiſe of aſſiſtance and acceptance; I now dedicate and deliver up my ſelf fully, freely, and for ever unto the Lord; I yield and reſign up my Soul with all its powers and faculties; my Body with all its ſenſes and members to be the inſtruments of righteouſneſs unto God: I reſign up my Minde to think upon the Lord, and thoſe things which concern his Intereſt and Glory, to receive, embrace and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his Truths; I reſign up my Memory, to be a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:154091:38"/> ſtore-houſe and receptacle chiefly of the great things which do belong to his Kingdom, and other things of a more inferiour rank, as they may have a refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence unto his Glory. I reſign up my Conſcience to receive light and purity from his Word and Spirit, and deſire that it may act faithfully as the Lords De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty. I reſign up my Will unto the Will of God, to ſubmit to his Precepts, to embrace his Promiſes, to oppoſe what he hath forbidden, to comply with all the diſpenſations of his Providence towards me, to be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that I ſhould be, and do, and bear, and chooſe and loſe what God would have me. I reſign up my Heart and Affections to fear and reverence the Lord, to believe and truſt in the Lord, to deſire and ſeek after the Lord, to love and delight in the Lord, and deſire to put them all under his Government, and to have them exerciſed according to his will. I reſign up my Fancy to be governed and employed by my Reaſon in the ſervice of my Maſter. I reſign up my Senſual Appetite after meat and drink, ſleep, and any pleaſures to be ſubſervient to my Rational Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, and no further to have ſatisfacton, than will tend to the glory of the Lord. I reſign up my Hands to work for God, my Feet to walk for God, my Ears to hear for God, my Eyes to ſee for God, my Tongue to ſpeak for God. I reſign up all my Graces, all my Gifts, all my Talents, to be uſed for the Glory of my Lord and Maſter; and my whole Man to be ruled and governed by his Laws: Promiſing, though my Fleſh do contradict and rebell, that I will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to order my whole converſation according to his Word; humbly looking up to him for ſtrength ſo to doe, that I may be enabled by him to every duty. And now I look upon my ſelf no longer my own,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:154091:39"/> or that any thing I have is at my own diſpoſe; but I wholly belong unto the Lord: And therefore, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and praiſing, and giving thanks unto the Lord, for vouchſafing to enter into Covenant with me, and enclining my heart to enter into Covenant with him; Bending my neck under the feet of the moſt glorious Jehovah, I ſubſcribe my ſelf,</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <dateline>Witneſs my Hand and Seal.</dateline>
                                 <signed>The devoted Servant of the Lord, <hi>A. B.</hi>
                                 </signed>
                              </closer>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="direction">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Direct.</hi> 10. <hi>You muſt be ſtedfaſt, and perſevere in the wayes of God unto your lives end,</hi> if you would be ſaved: And here you muſt be ſtedfaſt,
<list>
                              <item>1. In the wayes of Truth.</item>
                              <item>2. In the Wayes of Gods Commandements.</item>
                           </list>
                        </p>
                        <p n="1">1. You muſt be ſtedfaſt and perſevere in <hi>the wayes of Truth;</hi> in the belief of the Truths of the Word, without turning aſide into wayes of Errour; there are wayes of Errour which will lead you as certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and more ſecurely to Hell, than the wayes of open profaneneſs. The Apoſtle tells us of damnable errours, as well as open, damnable ſins, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 1. and we read of ſome that are damned for believing a lye, that their deluſion hath been the cauſe of their damnation, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 11, 12. The Devil leads as many as he can in the cords of more groſs and known ſins towards the place of endleſs miſery; but
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:154091:39"/> if any of them begin to perceive their thraldom and danger, if their eyes be a little opened, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience awakened, and hearts affected, and they are perſwaded to look after their ſalvation, then he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to draw them into wayes of Errour, he hath his Agents and Miniſters, who are very ſubtle and crafty, and lye in wait to deceive, who with good words and fair ſpeeches inſinuate poyſonous doctrines; and pretending more glorious diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, higher and more excellent wayes, draw them out of the way of the Word and Ordinances, into paths of darkneſs, where they wander and loſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for ever; where they are toſſed up and down, and beaten to and fro with every winde of doctrine unto the ſhipwrack of their Faith and their Souls. As you hope for ſalvation, you muſt take heed of Errour; diligently inquire after Truth; ſearch for it as for ſilver, and digg for it as for hidden treaſures; digg for it in the golden Mines of the Scriptures, let the Word of God be the only Rule of your Faith; and having found the Truth, keep it, hold it faſt, labour to fix it in your mindes, let it be as a girdle about your loins; lay it up in your heart, let it be rooted there; apply your ſelves to Chriſt as a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to lead you by his Word and Spirit into all Truth, and to keep you from being deceived and deluded; and keep cloſe to the Miniſtery and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Chriſts Inſtitution, which the Lord hath appointed to continue unto the end of the World, for the edifying eſtabliſhment, and perfecting of the Saints, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 11, 12, 13, 14.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. You muſt be ſtedfaſt, and perſevere in <hi>the wayes of Gods Commandements;</hi> you muſt patiently
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:154091:40"/> continue in well-doing, if you would obtain im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal glory, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 7. you muſt endure to the end, if you would be ſaved, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 22. you muſt be faithfull unto the death, if you would gain the Crown of life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 10. It is abſolutely neceſſary unto ſalvation, that you hold out in the wayes of God; none but ſuch which come to the end of the race will obtain the prize; the Gate of Heaven lyeth at the further not the hither end of the Holy Path; therefore you muſt ſtedfaſtly perſevere in this way; if you ſhould fall down, you muſt riſe again, and go on; if you ſhould fall back or through miſtake turn aſide, you muſt return again, and make the more haſte; but if you ſhould fall off, if you ſhould fall away (as ſome have done who have ſeemed very zealous and forward Chriſtians as to the outward Profeſſion) you are loſt, you are caſt-awayes, and you will tumble and fall down into the bottomleſs Pit, from whence there is no returning. Be not then followers of them that draw back to perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but of them that believe to the ſaving of the Soul, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 39. Be followers of them who through faith and patience inherit the Promiſes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 12. It is a glorious Inheritance that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, that is promiſed and prepared in Heaven, let this encourage you to diligence and perſeverance unto the end; I ſhall conclude with the words of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 58. <hi>Therefore my beloved Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren be ſtedfaſt, unmoveable, alwayes abounding in the work of the Lord, foraſmuch as ye know that your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is not in vain in the Lord.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Thus I have given you Directions, <hi>What things you muſt do that you may be ſaved.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:154091:40"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <div n="3 cont." type="part">
                  <div n="2" type="section">
                     <p>II. THE Second and laſt thing for your guidance in the way of Salvation, is, <hi>To ſhew you what Means you muſt make uſe of to help you in theſe things.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There are Ten Means to be uſed in order to the attaining of Salvation:
<list>
                           <item>1. Self-examination.</item>
                           <item>2. Reading the Word of God, and other good books.</item>
                           <item>3. Hearing the Word Preached.</item>
                           <item>4. Meditation.</item>
                           <item>5. Prayer.</item>
                           <item>6. Chriſtian-conference.</item>
                           <item>7. Watchfulneſs.</item>
                           <item>8. Sanctification of Faſting-dayes.</item>
                           <item>9. Sanctification of Sabbath-dayes.</item>
                           <item>10. Improvement of Sacrament-dayes.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <div n="1" type="means">
                        <p>Means 1. <hi>Self-examination.</hi> You muſt examine your ſelves, if you would ſee your ſelves loſt; you may read the miſtake of the <hi>Laodiceans, Rev.</hi> 3. 17. <hi>Thou ſayeſt, I am rich, and encreaſed in goods, and have need of nothing; and knoweſt not that thou art wretched, miſerable, and poor, and blinde, and naked.</hi> You muſt examine and prove your ſpiritual ſtate, that you may have a right judgement thereof, that you may perceive how poor, and wretched, and miſerable you are whileſt you are in a ſtate of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. You muſt examine your ſelves, that you may get a ſight and ſenſe of ſin: <hi>Jer.</hi> 8. 6. <hi>I hearkned and heard, but they ſpake not aright, no man repented
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:154091:41"/> him of his wickedneſs, ſaying, What have I done? every one turned to his courſe, as the Horſe ruſheth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the battel.</hi> You muſt examine what you have done, if you would repent of your ſins; you muſt ſearch and try your wayes, if you would turn from your evil wayes; you muſt commune with your hearts, and come to your ſelves, with the Prodigal, if you would return unto God, and turn your feet unto his Teſtimonies. Be ſerious then in this great duty of Self-examination; and that you may be ſo, I would adviſe that you would ſet apart time for it, when your thoughts are moſt free, and affections moſt ſedate and quiet; get out of the hurry of the world, and lay aſide other buſineſs for a while; and withall ſeparate your ſelves from company, and retire into ſecret, where you may be free from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal diſturbances and interruptions; whatever in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſitions and withdrawments of heart you finde, force your ſelves to the work; reſiſt Satan, who will endeavour to divert and diſcourage you: Set your ſelves in the preſence of God; deſire him to ſearch you; beg his help in the duty; labour to keep your minde cloſe to it; if vain thoughts ariſe, and would hurry you away, look up to Chriſt to rebuke them, and to bring them into captivity and obedience unto himſelf. And then ſit down, and ſeriouſly conſider what you have done ever ſince you came into the World, and withall think with your ſelves what you will do when your life and this world ſhall come to an end. Take a review of your ſins; they are noted down upon the book of your Conſciences, peruſe this book; and if you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted a Catalogue of your ſins, it might be a help to you. Note down your original ſin; your actual
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:154091:41"/> ſins; your tranſgreſſions of Gods Law, in the firſt and the ſecond Table thereof; your diſobedience to the Goſpel; the aggravations of your ſins.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="means">
                        <p>Means 2. <hi>Reading the Word of God, and other good books.</hi> The rule whereby you are to examine your ſelves is the Word; this is like a Candle, which will give light in dark corners; this is like a Glaſs, which will diſcover ſpots in the face; you muſt ſearch the Word, and try your ſelves hereby, if you would have knowledge of ſin, and your ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſtate; and you muſt ſearch the Word, if you would have knowledge and acquaintance with God and his will. You may arrive to ſome knowledge of God by reading the Book of Nature; the whole world is full of God, and every Creature doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent him; but the world is full of ſin too, and the more immediate repreſentations of the Creatures are ſenſitive things, which our ſenſe layeth hold on firſt, and is apt there to ſtick, without further piercing and ſearching to finde out God; and where we have one provocation from the Creatures to love and ſerve him (through the bewitching temptations of the world, meeting with the worldly luſts of our hearts) we have a thouſand incitements and allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from them to ſin againſt God; but the Word is full of God, and no incitement there to ſin, full of perſwaſives to holineſs and obedience; God is to be ſeen more eaſily, and he ſetteth forth himſelf there moſt conſpicuouſly; In the Book of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures you have the moſt glorious diſcoveries of God, in his greatneſs, majeſty, power, holineſs, love, mercy, and the like; and the way made known of acquaintance and communion with him; if you
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:154091:42"/> would be acquainted with God in Chriſt, you muſt acquaint your ſelves with the Scriptures: Read the Scriptures daily, and ſearch them; <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 39. read not only the hiſtory of the Word, but labour to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the myſtery of Godlineſs therein revealed, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16. endeavour after a ſpiritual diſcerning of the things of the Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14. when you meet with Doctrines in your reading the Word, labour to underſtand and believe them; when you meet with Precepts labour to obey them; when with Prohibitions and Threatnings, be cautioned againſt ſin by them; when you meet with promiſes, labour to apply them, to draw vertue from them. Read this Book as the Word of God, and hide it in your heart; lay it up there, as a choice treaſure, get your hearts caſt into the mould of it; get it written upon your hearts, and let it have an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon your whole converſation; and that you may the better underſtand and apply the truths of the Word, read as you have time other good books, which open the Scriptures, and treat of need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full points of Religion, eſpecially ſuch as direct in the great work of Converſion, and give Rules out of the Word for the ordering of your whole conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; but above all Books read and ſtudy the Scriptures.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="means">
                        <p>Means 3. <hi>Hearing the Word Preached.</hi> It is by the fooliſhneſs of Preaching that God ſaveth ſuch as do believe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 21. however the preaching of the Word is to them that periſh fooliſhneſs, yet unto Believers it is the power of God unto ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; therein God doth put forth his power, and maketh bare his arm, in bringing ſalvation to loſt
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:154091:42"/> ſouls. <hi>Hear and thy Soul ſhall live,</hi> Iſa. 55. 3. <hi>Faith cometh by hearing,</hi> Rom. 10. 17. <hi>Lydia</hi>'s heart was opened whileſt ſhe attended upon the Word preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 16. 14. Attend therefore diligently upon the Word preached by Chriſts Miniſters, as an Ordinance of his own inſtitution for the working and increaſe of Grace: Look upon Miniſters as Chriſts Ambaſſadours; he that heareth them hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Chriſt, and he that turneth away his ear from hearing them, turneth away his ear from Chriſt, who by his Spirit in them ſpeaketh from Heaven unto men, and how impoſſible it is for ſuch to eſcape the wrath of God, ſee <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 25. <hi>Much more ſhall not they eſcape that turn away their ear from him that ſpeaketh from Heaven.</hi> Hear the Word with reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, as the Word of God, as if the Lord ſhould ſpeak to you from Heaven with an audible voice; hear the Word with diligence and attention as for your lives, as for the ſalvation of your Souls; hear the Word with faith and love, without which it will not profit and work effectually in your hearts; and in hearing look not ſo much for thoſe things which may pleaſe, as for that which may edifie; I mean, do not regard ſo much mens fancies, as the wholſom Truths of the Word, which tend moſt to conviction, edification, to the killing of ſin, quickning and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Grace, and nouriſhment of the ſpiritual life.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="means">
                        <p>Means 4. <hi>Meditation.</hi> The Word like Food muſt be digeſted by Meditation, that it may turn to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual nouriſhment; you muſt ponder and conſider in your mindes the Truths of the Word, that you may both underſtand them, and get your Hearts affected
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:154091:43"/> with them, and your Lives ordered by them. Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is a great help in Heavens way, ſuch as are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs herein cannot walk ſo ſteddily, nor chearfully; accuſtome your ſelves unto this duty, ſet apart time for it; I know that ſome complain of barrenneſs in their thoughts, when they endeavour to meditate; ſuch I would adviſe, if they have not that fruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thoughts themſelves to ſupply them with matter, that they would make uſe of others help; let them meditate on the Scriptures they read, on the Sermons they hear; moreover I would offer ſome general heads for Meditation, which you may make uſe of. 1. Sometimes meditate on God, his Attributes, his infinite Majeſty, power, holineſs, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipreſence, omniſcience, eternity, unchangeableneſs, his infinite wiſdom, truth, faithfulneſs, juſtice, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, mercy and loving-kindneſs; his Councels, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially his eternal decree of Election, which is of moſt ſweet conſideration to Believers; his works of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and Providence. 2. Sometimes meditate on Chriſt; his near relations, of Friend, Brother, Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; his needfull Offices of Prieſt, Prophet, and King. 3. Sometimes meditate on the Spirit, his way and workings on the minde and heart, how he enlighteneth, enliveneth, ſtrengtheneth, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 4. Sometimes meditate on the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, and the rich, free, ſuitable, ſure Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of pardon, grace, ſalvation therein. 5. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times meditate on the Goſpel, and its priviledges, Juſtification, Adoption, Sanctification, Aſſurance of Gods love, peace of Conſcience, Joy in the Holy Ghoſt, communications of grace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 6. Sometimes meditate on the four laſt things, namely, Death, Judgement, Heaven and Hell. 7. Sometimes medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:154091:43"/> and that frequently, daily, of ſuch Arguments as tend to the mortifying of your particular ſins, which are moſt ſtrong and prevalent, and to the ſtrengthening of your graces which you finde moſt weak and deficient.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="means">
                        <p>Means 5. <hi>Prayer.</hi> Pray <hi>ſecretly;</hi> retire your ſelves from company into your Cloſets, or ſome private place, and there confeſs your ſins, and make known your requeſts to God, that ſeeth and heareth in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, and hath promiſed an open reward to ſuch as ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly and ſincerely ſeek him. Pray <hi>frequently,</hi> be often upon your knees, give your ſelves unto Prayer; begin the day, conclude the day with Prayer, and recover ſome other time to viſit and ſpeak to God; at leaſt mingle ejaculatory Prayer with every other work; and labour that your minds may be always in a praying frame; and do not withdraw, but be glad when an opportunity offereth it ſelf to come to the throne of grace. Pray <hi>fervently,</hi> pour forth your hearts before God in the duty; wreſtle with God in Prayer like <hi>Jacob,</hi> be earneſt in your Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as for your lives, be inſtant and importunate, take no denyal, follow hard after God; ſtir up your ſelves to take hold on him, uſe arguments in Prayer, to plead with him. Pray <hi>believingly,</hi> mingle your prayers with Faith; make uſe of the name and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of Jeſus Chriſt; and make application of the Promiſes which God hath made to his People, which he hath made to Faith, and which he hath made to Prayer.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="means">
                        <p>Means 6. <hi>Chriſtian Conference.</hi> Take heed of the company of the wicked; from ſuch turn away; if
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:154091:44"/> you are under tyes to be in ſuch company, converſe with them as infected perſons, with an Antidote, leſt you receive hurt by them, and with endeavours of doing them good. But chooſe the company of them that fear God; they are the excellent perſons; the wicked are the Droſs of the Earth, they are the Gold; let your delight be in their ſociety; aſſociate chiefly, if you have opportunity, with ſuch as have moſt of the power of godlineſs; and labour to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove by their company whenever you come into it; endeavour to get light, and life, and warmth and ſtrength from them; take heed of unprofitable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; but let it be with grace for edification.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="means">
                        <p>Means 7. <hi>Watchfulneſs.</hi> Watch unto duty; there are ſome golden ſeaſons for ſome duties, ſome choice opportunities of doing and receiving good, which if once ſlipt, you may never have the like again ſo long as you live; watch that you may know them, watch that you may improve them; underſtand the day of your viſitation; ſow your ſeed whileſt the weather laſteth; hoiſt up the ſail when the wind bloweth; watch the breathings of the Spirit, and comply with its motions. Watch againſt ſin, and therefore keep your hearts with all diligence; guard your ſenſes; take heed of Satan; get on the Spiritual Armour, eſpecially the ſhield of Faith, and fight the good fight of Faith, that you may lay hold on eternal life.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="means">
                        <p>Means 8. <hi>Sanctification of Faſting-dayes.</hi> Set apart times to humble your Souls before God in Faſting, and Prayer; and therein rend your hearts and not your garments; labour to afflict your Souls for ſin; meet God with weeping and ſupplication; cloathe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:154091:44"/> your ſelves with humility, lie in the duſt, cover your ſelves with ſhame; loath and abhorr your ſelves in his ſight for your iniquities, mourn for your own ſins, and for the great diſhonours of his Name by the ſins of others: And ſeek to the Lord both for your ſelves, and for his Church.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="means">
                        <p>Means 9. <hi>Sanctification of Sabbath-dayes.</hi> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to keep holy the Sabbath-day; break off timely the day before from worldly employments, and be earneſt with God to prepare your heart for the day; and when the day is come, begin and hold on with God from Morning to Night, in the publick, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and ſecret duties of his immediate Worſhip, except what time works of neceſſity and mercy do call for: Labour to be in the Spirit and in the fear of God all the day long; lay aſide worldly buſineſs, take heed of vain and unprofitable diſcourſe; let not the Duties of Religion ſeem tedious, but call the Sabbath your delight; begin Heaven-work on ſuch dayes, that you may be fitted by theſe Sabbaths for the Eternal Reſt: Praiſe God on theſe dayes for the works of Creation, eſpecially for the work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption; and labour to grow in grace by the dews of the Word which fall upon you moſt plentifully on ſuch dayes.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="means">
                        <p>Means 10. <hi>Improvement of Sacrament-dayes.</hi> Come frequently to the Table of the Lord, if you have opportunity, to celebrate the Memorial of Chriſts Death, and come preparedly; examine your ſelves; pray for the Wedding-garment; read the hiſtory of Chriſts Paſſion; conſider ſuch arguments as may be a means to draw forth your graces into exerciſe;
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:154091:45"/> and when you are there, labour to mourn for ſin, which hath pierced the Lord; to hunger after his righteouſneſs; to receive him by Faith; to apply the Promiſes of the Covenant of Grace, whereof the Sacrament is a Seal; endeavour after a burning love to him whoſe love hath been ſo great as to dye for you; and let your hearts be filled with joy, and your mouths with Praiſes, and deliver up your ſelves in Covenant unto the Lord in this Ordinance; After you come from the Lords Table, reflect upon your carriage towards the Lord; if you have been ſtraitened, endeavour to find out the cauſe, mourn, and by after-pains and application of Chriſt, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to get ſome benefit, and prepare better againſt the next time; if you have been enlarged, be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, be thankfull, be watchfull, live up to Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; draw vertue from Chriſts death for the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying more and more of your fleſh, with its affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and luſts; and fetch influences of grace and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual nouriſhment, that you may encreaſe with the encreaſes of God.</p>
                        <p>Finally, be diligent in the uſe of theſe, and all other means and helps, and ſo at length you ſhall attain the ultimate end, for which they are appointed, even your Salvation and Eternal Happineſs.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:154091:45"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154091:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
